<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog.rss" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-03-04T14:00:05-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog.rss</id><title type="html">Micah Redding</title><subtitle>I&apos;m Micah Redding. I grew up as a preacher&apos;s kid, and traveled the world as a rock musician.  Now I develop software — and write about religion, technology, and the future of human life.</subtitle><author><name>{&quot;twitter&quot;=&gt;&quot;micahtredding&quot;}</name></author><entry><title type="html">Life at Scale</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/life-at-scale/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Life at Scale" /><published>2021-03-24T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-03-24T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/life-at-scale</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/life-at-scale/"><![CDATA[<p>Life as we know it is full of incredible diversity and change. From single-cell to multi-cellular organisms, from asexual reproduction to sexual recombination, from bacteria to plants to fungi to vertebrates, life evolves, transforms, and grows before our eyes. It produces species like the blue whale, the coral reef, and the human being. More, it produces symbiotic networks, dynamic biological relationships between everything from cooperative genes to intertwined ecosystems.</p>

<p>We stand on the verge of this life spreading beyond our planet. Humans have set foot on the Moon, and will soon set foot on other worlds. With us, we will bring life: bacteria, plants, microorganisms, and eventually trees, grasses, birds, and fish. From these beginnings, new ecosystems will grow. World after world will bloom into life, and develop and be developed in its own unique way. We will learn new things about the growth and cultivation of ecosystems, and this knowledge will be used to help the ecosystem of Earth survive and flourish.</p>

<p>In the process, perhaps we will create unique habitats for particular species, turning “endangered” on its head, and giving them new worlds in which to flourish. Planets of whales, buffalos, and mammoths; planets designed for previously extinct species; planets designed to explore the incredible capacities of life itself.</p>

<p>But life will not stop there. As we’ve seen with our own planet, life will soon integrate and connect at larger scales, until there is a higher-order web of life playing out across our solar system. New modes and forms of life will arise, and create dynamic transformation and feedback across the worlds.</p>

<p>And then, eventually, life will spread to the stars. First one, then another, then another—star systems will “wink on” with light and life reaching back out to us, sharing new discoveries and creations. These systems may recapitulate on a smaller scale the history of life in this solar system, beginning on one planet, then gradually growing to become interplanetary. By the time they span their own solar systems, the possibility of interstellar life will have arisen, and tentative connections and dynamic exchange will have begun between the stars.</p>

<p>This process will continue, with new distances and new scales and new forms of life. At each level, the logic of life itself will drive onward and upward. But the only inevitability in this process is growth and change and transformation; each living being, entity, and ecosystem will be unique and free, exploring the full diversity of the possibilities of life. This is what makes life so incredibly significant and valuable: it holds agency within itself—it is embodied freedom and exploration. And this is why it will continue: because new modes and new forms of life are possible, and the exploration must go on.</p>

<p>And so it will continue, and new creatures will arise and populate new worlds, until life is acting at the scale of galaxies and superclusters and universes.  The cosmos will have come to life, knit together in a vast cosmic web of freedom and creativity and exploration.</p>

<p>This life will continually bring forth new living worlds, living galaxies, and perhaps even living cosmos_es_. Physicist Lee Smolin has hypothesized that black holes are baby universes, and that our universe may itself have emerged from a black hole within another universe. If so, then future cosmic life will use this process to create <em>living</em> baby universes, designed to bring forth an even greater diversity and breadth of life.</p>

<p>At this point, we step beyond the limits of our current comprehension. If there are greater worlds to explore, and more forms and modes of life to experience, then life will reach them. And unless something fundamental presents an unscalable barrier, life will keep rising, and exploring, and experiencing forever.</p>

<p>But this raises a set of questions. What are the characteristics and attributes of such life? What kind of life can survive and thrive at these scales? What are the things life will have to leave behind, and what are the things it will cling to?</p>

<p>I’ve come to believe the fundamental attributes of such life are relational values, such as trust, cooperation, and compassion. These in turn entail the values of freedom, diversity, and independence. The move outward, as embodied in all living things, entails the value of diversity and independence. The move upward, to connect into larger symbiotic networks and ecosystems, entails the value of connection and trust. When life not only embodies these values, but is fully and deeply conscious of them, then these values will shape the galaxies, and direct the orbit of stars.</p>

<p>But there is another value, entailed by these, but under-recognized and under-appreciated. That is <em>humility</em>. Humility is entailed by the willingness to transform and grow. Humility is entailed by the willingness to cooperate and trust. Humility is entailed by the willingness to let others explore and change. Humility is the bedrock of science, baked into it at a fundamental level, far deeper than the superficial arrogance of many of its practitioners. And humility is the defining character of the life that will span all things.</p>

<p>This life will have to stoop, to bend, to kneel—over and over again, as a gardener with a plant, as a farmer with the soil, as a parent with a child. This life will look from on high with joy at new life springing forth; and this life will then stoop to meet it, to embrace it, to raise it up. That will involve risk, and it will involve trust, and it will involve being willing to change. And thus, it will involve humility.</p>

<p>This is the nature of the life that will span all things. It will embody compassion, cooperation, and trust. It will embody exploration, diversity, and freedom. It will embody humility and transformation. It will embody love.</p>

<p>If life as a whole does not end soon, then this kind of future will unfold in front of us. And we will have the glorious opportunity to rise and participate in it.</p>

<p>And as we do so, we will be pressed to consider the possibility that elsewhere in the multiverse, this kind of life is already growing, surviving, and thriving at scales beyond our wildest imagination.</p>]]></content><author><name>Micah Redding</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Life as we know it is full of incredible diversity and change. From single-cell to multi-cellular organisms, from asexual reproduction to sexual recombination, from bacteria to plants to fungi to vertebrates, life evolves, transforms, and grows before our eyes. It produces species like the blue whale, the coral reef, and the human being. More, it produces symbiotic networks, dynamic biological relationships between everything from cooperative genes to intertwined ecosystems.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://res.cloudinary.com/micahredding/image/upload/v1616619665/3599135900_2887f93c71_o_kjxaj2.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://res.cloudinary.com/micahredding/image/upload/v1616619665/3599135900_2887f93c71_o_kjxaj2.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Origins of Transhumanism: W.D. Lighthall</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/origins-of-transhumanism-wd-lighthall/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Origins of Transhumanism: W.D. Lighthall" /><published>2021-02-09T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2021-02-09T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/origins-of-transhumanism-wd-lighthall</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/origins-of-transhumanism-wd-lighthall/"><![CDATA[<p>For several years now, I’ve been hunting the origins of transhumanism. One of the significant mysteries in this story is the first time the word “transhumanism” shows up in English.</p>

<p>Until recently, the first appearance of “transhumanism”, was credited to Julian Huxley’s 1957 essay of the same name. Here, Huxley proposes a new philosophy of humanity, seemingly coining both the word and the philosophy at the same time:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The human species can, if it wishes, transcend itself — not just sporadically, an individual here in one way, an individual there in another way, but in its entirety, as humanity. We need a name for this new belief. Perhaps transhumanism will serve: man remaining man, but transcending himself, by realizing new possibilities of and for his human nature.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Huxley, however, was friends with <a href="https://www.vice.com/en/article/nz7z7q/the-priest-who-believed-in-god-and-the-singularity-pierre-teilhard-de-chardin">Pierre Teilhard de Chardin</a>, and wrote the forward to Teilhard’s book “Phenomenon of Man” (published in 1955, written in the 1930s). In his forward, he praises Teilhard’s thought, but expresses a wish to separate himself from Teilhard’s religious roots.</p>

<p>It would not be much of a stretch to see Huxley’s transhumanism as a secularized version of Teilhard’s vision. And in fact, Teilhard himself was already using similar terms. In 1949, Teilhard de Chardin was using words like “trans-humanizing” and “trans-humanity”:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Liberty: that is to say, the chance offered to every man (by removing obstacles and placing the appropriate means at his disposal) of ‘ <strong>trans-humanizing</strong> ’ himself by developing his potentialities to the fullest extent. (The Future of Mankind, 1949)</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>In consequence one is the less disposed to reject as unscientific the idea that the critical point of planetary Reflection, the fruit of socialization…represents…not an ending of the ultra-human but its accession to some sort of <strong>trans-humanity</strong> at the ultimate heart of things. (The Future of Mankind, 1951)</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This suggests a prior history for both the word and the concepts. And indeed, Peter Harrison and Joseph Wolyniak have tracked down a prior use of the term, in W. D. Lighthall’s 1940 essay for the Royal Society of Canada: “The Law of Cosmic Evolutionary Adaptation: An Interpretation of Recent Thought”.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, this work has been incredibly hard to get hold of. It appears to remain in only one or two research libraries, undigitized, and inaccessible to public view. At one point, I sent someone to one of these libraries to take a look, and when the research librarians went to retrieve it, the work had gone missing.</p>

<p>But today, after years of waiting, I was finally able to view a copy of its pages.</p>

<p>And I understand a bit more of its context.</p>

<p>W.D. Lighthall begins by arguing that evolution shows signs of purposiveness and direction, and that it emerged from the energy of the Sun—an energy that not only spreads in all directions, but which comes from a stellar phenomenon that is repeated endlessly throughout the universe.</p>

<p>Lighthall then argues that since light is pervasive across space and time, we should expect that life is also pervasive across space and time. Wherever radiation is met with adaptation, life shows up.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Rationally, the stars are as full of life as they are of light.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>But we should not think this life must be protein-based like our own. Indeed, all that is needed to serve as a substrate for life is the functional ability to receive and adapt. And so proteins must be part of a much larger family of living substrates.</p>

<p>And this tells us something about our own future. Contrary to the pessimism and fear that many scientists evoked about the future of the Solar System, Lighthall argues that radiation supports life, and so life will adapt to the future changes of radiation, growing stronger and more elevated no matter what those changes are.</p>

<p>And this means the future of life is not just safe, but radically expanded.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>And, since all the newly discovered cosmic bodies can be our future realm, there comes the aspiration of a New Empire for the human race, not limited to some vegetation on Mars, some phase of water, or a scanty oxygen, on Venus…
What shall be our locomotion through that New Empire? Certainly not by our protein bodies. Is it presumably by that electronic locomotion by which we arrived from the Sun…</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The forms of motion through the cosmos are unlimited. The substrates that we may bring to life are unbounded. The joys that await life on the cosmic stage are infinite.</p>

<p>And the fact that this awaits us is closely connected to the fact that life must have already attained it. Life reaches far beyond us, and owing to its unlimited age and pervasiveness in time, it reaches far above us as well.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Logically, owing to its infinite age and its varied immensity, it should contain far more marvellous beneficent and progressive devices than its branch, the protein Terrestrial Evolutionary Adaptation, which is a young offshoot.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The expectation that this is true is what fuels our confidence that we may expect this for our future—that we can rise to participate in the glory and wonder of life at unlimited scale.</p>

<p>Thus, our confidence in Life is a confidence in unlimited progression.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I look to the Cosmic Source of all earthly thought as the necessary Director of larger thought in the Cosmos; and to the Source of Progress in Cosmic Life for the vaster Goals of activity beyond, with fairer joys and unspeakable revelations, forever increasing.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It is in this context that Lighthall introduces the term “transhumanism”:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Over all, we should remember Dante’s supernal principle: 
<em>Trasumanar significar per verba Non si porria.</em> 
[“Words cannot tell of that transhuman change”]</p>

  <p>and Paul’s Transhumanism: “Eye has not seen, nor ear heard, neither has it entered into the conception of man.”</p>

  <p>Along the same line of thought, the reasons appear good in favour of Undying Life in the Cosmos.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Lighthall is arguing for nothing less than a cosmic Kingdom of Heaven. Life that reaches from the unimaginable heights of existence down to the cells of our bloodstreams. Life that is united by joy, and progress, and love.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>it is…always inventive, adaptive, progressive, and above all Affective, i.e. it deals with joy and pain. Its fundamental principle is the cosmic production of permanence and happiness, and flight from pain and destruction.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>In evoking Paul and Dante, Lighthall is arguing that the ascendence of life has no limits, and far exceeds our imagination. And that, just as in Paul and Dante, the very nature of this transcendence assures us of our own place within it.</p>

<p>In the verse that Lighthall is quoting, Paul is not simply saying that there is more than we can currently imagine—he’s saying that more than we can currently imagine awaits <em>us</em>.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Ethically, this picture fits well into the essentials of Christianity—itself the highest product of the Terrestrial Evolution. Jesus, the Scholar of the lily, the sparrow, and the Kingdom of the Father, was this kind of an Evolutionist.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This is where it all leads. For Lighthall, all existence is contained within an infinite, expanding ecosystem, a cosmic Kingdom of Heaven, knit together by unthinkable modes and forms of life—a life that we humans are invited to rise and participate in. And in such a universe, we could have no better teacher and guide than the one who saw in lilies and sparrows, the very principles of everlasting life.</p>

<p>It appears, then, that we stand near one of the significant headwaters of transhumanism.</p>

<p>Here we have a source that anticipates substrate-independent life, that imagines interstellar travel, that assumes life may adapt and thrive far beyond the death of our solar system, that imagines minds both radically different and deeply similar to our own, and that anticipates our transformation into creatures beyond all known limits.</p>

<p>Here we have a source that seems to anticipate some of the ways the Simulation Argument and the Fermi Paradox connect questions about ultimate life with our own expectations of the future.</p>

<p>And here we have a source that is inspired by a combination of scientific understanding and religious visions.</p>

<p>This is a profound transhumanism. And as it stands today, it appears that the earliest known use of the term “transhumanism”—was describing a <em>Christian</em> Transhumanism.</p>

<p>~</p>

<hr />

<ul>
  <li>Julian Huxley. Transhumanism. The essay originally published in New Bottles for New Wine, London: Chatto &amp; Windus 1957, pp. 13-17</li>
  <li>Cole-Turner, Ron. 2015. “The History of the Word ‘Transhumanism.’” TheologyPlus: Theology Engaging Science and Technology. 2015. https://www.theologyplus.org/the-history-of-the-word-transhumanism/.</li>
  <li>Harrison, Peter, and Joseph Wolyniak. 2015. “The History of ‘Transhumanism.’” Notes and Queries. https://doi.org/10.1093/notesj/gjv080.</li>
  <li>W. D. Lighthall, ‘The Law of Cosmic Evolutionary Adaptation: An Interpretation of Recent Thought’, <em>Royal Society of Canada, Ottawa. Proceedings and Transactions / Me´moires et Comptes Rendus de la Socie´te´ Royale Du Canada</em> 1940. ser. 3, v. 34, section 2, 135–41.</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Micah Redding</name></author><category term="Transhuman" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[For several years now, I’ve been hunting the origins of transhumanism. One of the significant mysteries in this story is the first time the word “transhumanism” shows up in English.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://res.cloudinary.com/micahredding/image/upload/v1612920859/48792411147_bd2a8265d2_k_u85pbu.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://res.cloudinary.com/micahredding/image/upload/v1612920859/48792411147_bd2a8265d2_k_u85pbu.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Paul, Paradox, Myth, and the Danger of Knowledge</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/paul-paradox-myth/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Paul, Paradox, Myth, and the Danger of Knowledge" /><published>2020-03-22T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-03-22T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/paul-paradox-myth</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/paul-paradox-myth/"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p>“Paul, you are out of your mind! Your great learning is driving you mad!”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>So exclaimed the governor Festus on hearing Saint Paul speak.</p>

<p>Until recently, this statement made sense to me. Studying too much can push some people over the edge. But lately, I’ve started to wonder if the whole concept behind this outburst isn’t tied up with ancient paganism.</p>

<p>After all, shouldn’t learning be a good thing? Isn’t learning good for everyone?</p>

<p>Apparently, the ancient pagan world didn’t think so. The great philosophers taught the elite, the sons of kings. Plato advocated “benevolent deception” of others. Meanwhile, the Jews were instructed to teach their children, writing the most sacred information on their doorposts.</p>

<p>Maybe there’s something fundamental here. Maybe there’s something core to the ancient pagan worldview, that caused learning to be dangerous, toxic, self-limiting.</p>

<p>My mind is drawn to the statement “All Cretans are liars,” made by the Cretan Epimenides. This is called the <em>Epimenides Paradox</em>, and is interpreted as a form of the self-contradictory claim “This statement is false”.</p>

<p>Paul would have known about this logic puzzle. Whether or not the irony of the statement was intended by Epimenides’ original words, by Paul’s time, the logical form of the puzzle was already being discussed in the Greek world.</p>

<p>And interestingly, Paul quotes Epimenides twice in the New Testament.</p>

<p>The first is when he is standing in Athens, on Mars Hill, at the center of the Greek philosophical world. Here he makes a case for his form of monotheism, by citing a statement from Epimenides, “In him we live and move and have our being”.</p>

<p>The second is in Titus 1:12, where Paul quotes the source of the Epimenides Paradox itself—a statement that has been widely interpreted as meaning, “This statement is false”—and then follows it up with the mind-bending comment, “This statement is true”.</p>

<p>What is Paul doing? Is he letting us in on an incredibly nerdy philosophical joke? Is he affirming the paradox as fundamental in some way? Is he denying the interpretive premise of the paradox?  Is he telling us something about the pagan world?</p>

<p>Or is he doing all of the above?</p>

<p>In context, he’s warning against those who were peddling myths. In Athens, he was warning against those who were peddling idols. In both cases, he turns to Epimenides to speak to the problem.</p>

<p>The Epimenides Paradox relates to one of the most significant theorems in logic: Gödel’s Incompleteness Theorem. Gödel’s Theorem shows that there can ultimately be no closed, self-contained systems—because all systems contain something analogous to the Epimenides Paradox.</p>

<p>This shattered a long-held hope of philosophers and mathematicians. And was held to have wide-ranging social and philosophical consequences.</p>

<p>For example, some have suggested that Gödel overturns the very concept of a rule-based ethic. Once you establish a set of rules for determining right and wrong, then, per Gödel, you also establish a set of actions whose ethical value can never be determined.</p>

<p>In other words, Gödel may not just have shattered the dreams of mathematical philosophers, he may have shattered the dreams of millennia of religious scholars as well.</p>

<p>Douglas Hofstadter, in his famous book <em>Gödel Escher Bach</em>, argues that the power of this self-referencing circularity reveals something about consciousness and AI. Self-consciousness seems like the kind of self-referencing that leads to this paradox in the first place. And so Hofstadter, for hundreds of pages, strives to show us what self-reference really might contain.</p>

<p>But if this kind of self-referential circularity is so core to mathematics, to science, to consciousness itself—why is it so terrifying?</p>

<p>Because, as Gödel proves, this kind of circularity allows a system to destroy itself. A snake can eat its own tail. A Cretan can condemn his whole nation, and himself in the process.</p>

<p>This leaves you with only three options.</p>

<h4 id="one-burn-it-all-down">One, burn it all down.</h4>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Everything is meaningless! says the teacher.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>If no system can be consistent and complete, then there is no foundation to truth. It’s not turtles all the way down—a futile explanation for a futile problem—it’s simply nothingness, a leaning over the edge, a staring into the void.</p>

<h4 id="two-flinch">Two, flinch.</h4>

<p>Look away. Close your eyes. Pretend it’s not true.</p>

<p>If your system can’t be self-contained, just pretend it is, shout down the contrarians, destroy those who get in the way.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Better one man should die, than that the nation be destroyed.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>From the time of Cain til today, the great pagan dream was to build a walled city, a closed society, a self-contained system with no change, and no relationship to the outside world. This was the dream that drove Babel, and fueled Plato. This is what made the pagan gods torture Prometheus for bringing fire to man.</p>

<p>But no closed society can eradicate circularity, and thus every closed society is at risk of being destroyed.</p>

<p>Unless it can learn to lie.
Unless it can learn to look away.
Unless it can learn to question only so far—and then no farther.</p>

<p>A closed society creates a closed mind.</p>

<p>But a closed mind must work the same way. No outside thoughts, no outside forces. Everything needed is already contained within. You can search out ancient knowledge, you can study the known works, you can ask big questions. But question too much, and you might cross an invisible and dangerous line. You might invite in an outsider. You might find something troubling. You might unleash the chaos.</p>

<p>And so you learn to lie.
You learn to look away.
You learn to question only so far—and then no farther.</p>

<p>So you can see why, faced with something unheard of before, a leader in the ancient world would have assumed that in deep study, some unknown line had been crossed, and all chaos had broken loose.</p>

<p>Or…</p>

<h4 id="three-throw-open-the-gates">Three, throw open the gates.</h4>

<p>Build an open society, an open and evolving system, a system of concepts and symbols and meanings that make sense, but are not wholly self-contained, nor closed off to the outside world.</p>

<p>This system cannot eliminate circularity either. Instead, it must use circularity as an excuse to build outward, to embrace a stranger, to expand the circle of concern.</p>

<p><em>This statement is true</em>—and it is true within the larger sphere of life we must now embrace.</p>

<p>In Paul’s thought, the resurrection is not simply a moment in time where the ancient myths are reversed, and the dead refuse to stay dead. It is a moment in which the closed self-circularity of the world must break open, and infinite knowledge and learning and creation must pour in.</p>

<p>…</p>

<p><em>This essay assumes some familiarity with:</em></p>

<p><em><a href="https://amzn.to/3zMtKpi">Girard on Myth</a></em><br />
<em><a href="https://amzn.to/3fphweP">Popper on the Closed Society</a></em><br />
<em><a href="https://amzn.to/375rnBF">Hofstadter on Self-Reference and Paradox</a></em></p>]]></content><author><name>Micah Redding</name></author><category term="Theology" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[“Paul, you are out of your mind! Your great learning is driving you mad!”]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://res.cloudinary.com/micahredding/image/upload/v1627494433/serpent-adam-eve-classic.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://res.cloudinary.com/micahredding/image/upload/v1627494433/serpent-adam-eve-classic.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Teleology &amp;amp; Simulation</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/teleology-and-simulation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Teleology &amp;amp; Simulation" /><published>2020-02-20T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-02-20T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/teleology-and-simulation</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/teleology-and-simulation/"><![CDATA[<p><em>(—This essay is a draft, undergoing feedback and revision.—)</em></p>

<p>In 1802, William Paley famously set out the “Watchmaker Analogy”, a teleological argument, or <em>argument from design</em> for the existence of God.</p>

<p>The argument was as simple as it was intuitively compelling. Suppose you are walking alongside a river, and suddenly, you look down and see a pocket watch. In that moment, you know without a shadow of a doubt that this watch was deliberately <em>made</em>. There was a Watchmaker who created it.</p>

<p>This intuitive leap is bolstered by the fact that you can look at a thousand other objects lying on the banks of the river, and not come away with a similar impression. Design is something we recognize intuitively, and in recognizing it, also recognize that there had to be a designer.</p>

<p>This example seems relatively uncontroversial. But of course Paley was trying to make a bigger point: When we look at the natural world, with creatures who see, swim, fly, and dig, we intuitively recognize the presence of design. We understand that these things show the existence of <em>purpose</em>. Teeth are made for biting, wings are made for flying, and something must have intended that it be so.</p>

<p>Thus, there must be a Watchmaker for the natural world as well.</p>

<p>This argument has come up against strong criticism. Paley was writing in 1802, but by 1859, Darwin had published his theory on the origin of species, forever changing the nature of the discussion. Darwin seemed to provide an answer to Paley, and in fact, Richard Dawkins, in his book “The Blind Watchmaker”, famously claimed that this is exactly what had happened. Natural Selection had shown that non-purposive processes can lead to seemingly purposive results.</p>

<p>The argument seems to have reached a stalemate. It’s still intuitively compelling to many people, and yet, it is largely unconvincing to anyone educated in the natural sciences.</p>

<p>Let’s see if there’s a way to move forward.</p>

<h3 id="what-the-argument-from-design-actually-means">What the Argument from Design actually means</h3>

<p>Why is it that we recognize a pocket watch as designed? What are we actually recognizing when we do so?</p>

<p>A number of people have tried to spell out an answer in terms of complexity. But complexity is notoriously hard to quantify, and this path has produced few, if any, real results. I want to suggest a different approach.</p>

<p>I want to suggest we’re actually identifying two things:</p>

<ol>
  <li>This object is improbable</li>
  <li>This object is useful to a being like myself</li>
</ol>

<p>How do we know this object is improbable? Almost certainly, it’s because we’ve tried to create similar things before. We understand just how difficult it is to shape metal in this way, to wind springs, to construct gears. It’s no coincidence Paley formulated his analogy in the context of a society that was very good at making pocket watches. His readers intuitively understood what kinds of difficulties were involved.</p>

<p>So with the criteria of usefulness. How do we know this object is useful? It’s almost certainly because we’ve used something like it ourselves. We understand the utility of watches in an industrial society, we understand the value of making them portable, we understand the value of using compact symbols and dials to represent the passage of time.</p>

<p>Our Bronze Age ancestors probably would be able to recognize something similar. Shaped metal, glass, writing, numbers—all point to something they would have understood in terms of usefulness-to-humans-like-them. They probably would not immediately recognize the function of the device, but they would be able to understand it as the kind of things humans do.</p>

<p>Our hunter-gatherer ancestors? This is harder to picture. I guess that they would recognize some aspects of human design, and some aspects of something bizarre and unknown. In so doing, they would recognize the presence of something like themselves—and something very unlike themselves.</p>

<p>The point is, this intuition is not something intrinsic to certain kinds of objects in the natural world. It’s an intuition that comes from within <em>us</em>, and our role as creators of objects.</p>

<p>But why would the recognition of usefulness, indicate that beings-like-ourselves were involved? “A million monkeys pounding on typewriters will eventually produce the works of Shakespeare”, so the saying goes, so how do we know that some random series of events didn’t just throw up a pocket watch onto the shore?</p>

<p>Here, we’ve come to a probabilistic argument.</p>

<p>Presumably, a series of random collisions in a river, happening over trillions of years, would throw up a pocket watch onto the shore. But you’d be waiting an awfully long time.</p>

<p>On the other hand, if there is a society of beings-like-us around, and they are inventing and manufacturing things that they find useful, it’s likely that trillions of such objects are going to be spread throughout the world.</p>

<p>To put it more precisely: Intelligent beings will construct things that are difficult to make, but useful to them, at a rate unimaginably higher than natural processes alone.</p>

<p>So if you’re walking along one day, and discover an object that seems difficult to make, and would be useful for a being-like-yourself—then chances are trillions to one that you’ve discovered something made by a being-like-yourself.</p>

<p>This is what our intuition is identifying. The usefulness of this object to beings-like-ourselves indicates something about the choices beings-like-ourselves will likely make. This in turn indicates what they will turn their intelligence to. And where intelligence is, natural processes become statistically irrelevant.</p>

<p>This is actually a good short-hand definition for “intelligence”: Intelligence dramatically accelerates the creation of useful things.</p>

<p>So let’s call this the Expanded Argument from Design:</p>

<h3 id="expanded-argument-from-design">Expanded Argument from Design</h3>

<ol>
  <li>Our own experience (namely, what is difficult to create, and what is useful to create) gives us insight into both the natural world, and the psychology of beings-like-ourselves.</li>
  <li>In identifying an object as Difficult to Create, we are suggesting that the natural rate of occurrence of this object in nature is low.</li>
  <li>In identifying an object as Useful to Create, we are suggesting that the rate of creation of this object among beings-like-ourself is high.</li>
  <li>Thus, in identifying an object as something we would find Difficult to Create and Useful to Create, we are identifying that object as something produced at an unimaginably higher rate by beings-like-ourselves, than by natural processes alone.</li>
  <li>Thus, in identifying an object as something we would find Difficult to Create and Useful to Create, we are identifying the likely action of beings-like-ourselves.</li>
</ol>

<p>Note that at no point are we suggesting the impossibility of the natural occurrence of apparent design. Our argument here is simply about rates of occurrence. If we wanted to bring this into engagement with the phenomenon of natural selection, for example, we would want to compare the expected rate of what natural selection is producing, vs the expected rate of what intelligent beings might produce.</p>

<p>More on this below.</p>

<h3 id="the-simulation-argument">The Simulation Argument</h3>

<p>Having fleshed out the intuition that the Argument from Design is actually trading in, and having attempted to offer an expanded version of this argument, I want to now turn to something much more modern: <a href="https://www.simulation-argument.com">The Simulation Argument</a>.</p>

<p>For those who are unfamiliar, the Simulation Argument is based on the likelihood that, given somewhere between a few decades to a few more millennia, human civilization will start creating simulated (virtual, holographic, etc) worlds that are indistinguishable from the real thing. And, based on the way we already deal with simulated worlds (video games, virtual realities, etc), they will likely run trillions of these simulated worlds over time.</p>

<p>Presuming that many of these simulated worlds are like the one we live in now (after all, our descendants might want to visit our time in their equivalent of “Oregon Trail 3D”), then we reach a stunning conclusion:</p>

<p>It is likely that there are vastly more <em>simulated</em> worlds like our own, than there are “natural” worlds like our own.</p>

<p>And that leads us to the <em>Simulation Argument Trilemma</em>:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Almost all civilizations go extinct before simulating worlds like our own.</li>
  <li>Almost all civilizations are uninterested in simulating worlds like our own.</li>
  <li>You are almost certainly living in a simulation.</li>
</ol>

<p>I have dubbed this trilemma “Suicide, Censorship, or Simulation”. The first two are possible reasons for why no civilizations ever do this. The third is the consequence, assuming they do.</p>

<p>Assuming that some civilizations simulate worlds-like-our-own, then it is extremely likely that any given world-like-our-own exists inside a simulation.</p>

<p>Note that, contrary to many popular presentations, this is the <em>hopeful</em> option.</p>

<p>The first option is undesirable for obvious reasons. The second option is hard to imagine without picturing a very dire scenario—perhaps all simulations are forbidden by a totalitarian regime, or maybe worse, perhaps our descendants have no interest in us whatsoever.</p>

<p>The third option, however, is scariest for most people. What would it mean if we were living inside a simulation?</p>

<p>That’s another discussion. For now, let’s look at the underlying nature of this argument.</p>

<ol>
  <li>First, we observe that beings like ourselves have gone to great difficulties to simulate worlds, and that they show every indication of continuing to do this at an accelerating rate in the future.</li>
  <li>In identifying worlds-like-our-own as Difficult to Create, we are suggesting that the natural rate of occurrence of worlds-like-our-own is quite low.</li>
  <li>In identifying worlds-like-our-own as Useful to Create, we are suggesting that the rate of simulation of worlds-like-our-own by beings-like-ourself is quite high.</li>
  <li>Thus, in identifying worlds-like-our-own as Difficult to Create and Useful to Create, we are suggesting that worlds-like-our-own are produced at an unimaginably higher rate by beings-like-ourselves than by natural processes alone.</li>
  <li>Thus, in identifying worlds-like-our-own as Difficult to Create and Useful to Create, we are identifying our world as the likely product of beings-like-ourselves.</li>
</ol>

<p>This is the same basic argument as the Expanded Argument from Design. In both cases, we are extrapolating from our own psychology to the psychology of large numbers of beings like us. In both cases, we are looking at their likely behaviors. And in both cases, we are concluding from the simple probability of production numbers that we are likely witnessing the action of beings like ourselves.</p>

<p>The Simulation Argument Trilemma takes this as a starting point, and then offers two ways that our psychology might <em>not</em> reflect the psychology of future beings. First, those future beings might not exist. Second, they may have lost all interest in what interests us.</p>

<p>We can put this in the context of the Watchmaker Analogy. If we find a pocket watch, we assume it is the product of beings like ourselves.</p>

<p>But if we found out that the inhabitants of this planet had never developed the technology for shaping metal and glass, then we would be forced to conclude this apparent design was an illusion of some sort. Similarly, if we found out that the inhabitants of this planet had no interest in time whatsoever, then we would be forced to conclude that some other phenomenon was going on.</p>

<p>If both cases are hard to imagine, it’s because it is hard to imagine a psychology so different from ours. We know that in actual history, humans have produced millions and millions of pocket watches, and it’s almost impossible to think of it differently.</p>

<p>The Simulation Argument, on the other hand, is not yet as intuitive, because our simulations have not yet reached the precision and quality of the world we actually live in.</p>

<p>But if we keep creating as we have been, then soon, this intuition will change.</p>

<h3 id="the-hole-in-the-argument-from-design">The Hole in the Argument from Design</h3>

<p>There’s a crucial difference between the Argument from Design, and the Simulation Argument.</p>

<p>In the Watchmaker Analogy, we’re reasoning about the behavior of beings-like-us, in relationship to the production of pocket watches. We then attempt to turn our “pocket watch reasoning” onto the natural world, and reason about the behavior of beings-like-us in relation to it.</p>

<p>But this introduces a problem. We are unable to create a natural world. We cannot design wings or bones or teeth or claws from scratch. We thus find ourselves in the place of our hunter-gatherer ancestors: we can recognize something familiar here, but we cannot fully identify it.</p>

<p>We are trying to extrapolate from our own psychology—which can produce pocket watches—to the kind of superhuman psychology which can produce worlds.</p>

<p>Most devastatingly, we have not recognized that this is what we are doing. We assumed that the recognition of design was straight-forward, when it was actually an extrapolation of our own behavior and psychology.</p>

<p>This means that there’s a hole in the standard Argument from Design. We don’t intuitively understand the purposes of a superhuman psychology that can create a world. We thus don’t know what to look for, to identify its presence.</p>

<p>This is the hole that Darwin drove a train through.</p>

<p>Darwin’s picture did not look like what someone with our kind of psychology would come up with, and so it appeared that the argument from design had been overthrown.</p>

<p>The approach modeled in the Simulation Argument patches this hole. In the Simulation Argument, we explicitly identify the psychology of the beings we are trying to model, tease out the ways that psychology may differ from our own, and then extrapolate from their expected behavior.</p>

<p>This moves us from intuitive recognition to deliberative reasoning. Instead of asking whether we intuitively recognize the presence of design, we ask what purposes might drive beings who are greater than us.</p>

<p>Perhaps we conclude that no purposes of such beings would lead to a world like ours. Thus, we recognize no such design.</p>

<p>Or perhaps we recognize that there are purposes of superhuman beings that intersect deeply with the world we find ourselves in. And thus, we identify and confirm the design woven deeply and pervasively throughout our world.</p>

<h3 id="an-example">An Example</h3>

<p>I just want to give one example of the way this kind of reasoning might work, to take this from the abstract to something slightly concrete.</p>

<p>All life seems to be built on reproduction. Cells produce more cells, and when cells join together into multicellular organisms, those organisms produce new versions of themselves as well.</p>

<p>Interestingly, as life scales up, life seems to need to lean harder and harder into diversification. Single-celled-organisms can mutate, and so introduce some diversity, but sexual reproduction allows larger life-forms to embrace dramatic genetic changes from one generation to the next.</p>

<p>Arguably, humans have taken this to another level. Where horses and other creatures are born with almost all the skills they need to survive, human babies take a long time to develop those same skills—seeing, walking, feeding themselves, etc.</p>

<p>The fact that human babies are born in a <em>more infantile</em> state than other creatures, means that our primary abilities are all learned. And this means that we experience more dramatic changes from one generation to another than any other creature.</p>

<p>This is the secret of our success. We adapt, we invent, and we introduce dramatically new things all the time. We are born deeply dependent, and this is paradoxically how we become deeply independent.</p>

<p>This suggests a deep necessity at work. The more complex the organism, the more important it is to introduce diversification into its procreative process.</p>

<p>We must assume that any future civilization faces the same concerns. We can imagine a society spreading through space, seeding new worlds—and we must then assume that they are concerned that they do not simply clone an old world, but diversify, encouraging new kinds of life, and new directions in civilizational growth.</p>

<p>How might they do so?</p>

<p>One risky move—perhaps as risky as having offspring who take years to develop even the most basic survival skills—would be to drop human beings on a planet, and allow them to recapitulate the process of technological development.</p>

<p>This would ensure that an old world hadn’t simply been cloned, but that the rise of this new world would actually contribute something new and useful to the interstellar civilization. When they developed pervasive space-flight, then we might welcome them into our interstellar civilization.</p>

<p>We could imagine doing this in a few ways.</p>

<p>One way, we give them all of our technological knowledge, and allow them to study it and rebuild their world from scratch over roughly 50-100 years. This minimizes risk, but it maximizes sameness. They don’t end up making any real discoveries themselves, and so they don’t learn the kind of independence that will make them an asset to an interstellar civilization.</p>

<p>Another way would be to drop them on a planet, with a few basic starter ideas, and let them recapitulate the process of developing from hunter-gatherer society to global civilization. This is much more risky, and might take 10,000 years, but when they join interstellar civilization, they may have a lot more to offer.</p>

<p>We might imagine this process scaling up, as unimaginably powerful societies seed new planets, new star systems, new galaxies, new universes.</p>

<p>At each level, the society is faced with the question of how to grow new worlds, while introducing new kinds of diversification. The greater the scale, the more pressing the question becomes.</p>

<p>At the highest levels we can conceive, we might imagine a society seeding a new universe, watching for it to recapitulate the process of galactic, stellar, biological, intellectual, and technological evolution—eagerly awaiting what new things it will bring about.</p>

<p>Note that we actually have two concerns in these scenarios. We want “child societies” to grow and become independent, but we also want to make sure this isn’t abortive. We don’t want to invest 10,000 years growing a new planetary civilization, if it’s never going to get off the ground. So we have to figure out the sort of “minimum viable starter kit” for each level.</p>

<p>The same dilemma is played out in human biology. It’s important that we learn almost everything from scratch. But it’s also important we get the tools we need to learn. So both our biology and our culture tries to balance this out. Much of children’s initial learning is truly independent, but we try to “seed” their environment in a way that is maximally conducive to what we expect them to need.</p>

<p>So if some vast civilization is out there seeding universes, what might we expect to see?</p>

<p>We might expect to see a universe that seems uniquely fine-tuned for producing life.</p>

<p>We might expect to see a universe that seems uniquely comprehensible to intelligent beings. This might require it to be relatively “smooth”, so you can get a similar picture no matter where you are within it. This might require it to be relatively safe (few vast, fast-moving black holes). This might require it have interesting patterns to study at every scale.</p>

<p>We might expect to see a universe where life emerges very early in cosmic history, but has to develop from a single cell all the way to intelligent beings. We might expect to see each significant transition (non-existence to existence, non-life to life, non-intelligence to intelligence) happen almost exactly once.</p>

<p>And we might look at our universe, and notice that these are some of the most unusual and interesting facts about it.</p>

<p>Of course, what we make of this is wholly contingent on what we think superhuman psychology would produce, versus what we think we would expect to find without it.</p>

<p>And that’s an area for a lot more discussion.</p>

<h3 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h3>

<p>Paley’s reason for introducing the Watchmaker Analogy was to create a case for design from the observation of the natural world. He intuitively recognized that the natural world shows indications of being improbable, and yet meaningful to beings like us. We might assume then, that a being like us had a hand in it.</p>

<p>But the Simulation Argument shows us that this analysis is too limited. Yes, this kind of analysis works with pocket watches, but that doesn’t provide us with a linear path to anticipating the behavior of beings who have the power to create worlds.</p>

<p>Thus, in order to really grapple with the situation, we need to think about what those kinds of beings will want to do. Fortunately, our own future gives us a handle on some of those questions. We can tentatively approach them by asking what <em>we</em> will want to do in the future.</p>

<p>In order to determine whether the world we live in is the result of some form of design, we need to ask what we would do once we had the power to create a world. This may then allow us to identify the presence of design, and simultaneously challenge and improve our understanding of the psychology of beings who could create a world like our own.</p>

<hr />

<p><em>Thanks to Lincoln Cannon, Giulio Prisco, and Jonathan Gunnell for offering early comments on this essay.</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Micah Redding</name></author><category term="Theology" /><category term="Draft" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[(—This essay is a draft, undergoing feedback and revision.—)]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://res.cloudinary.com/micahredding/image/upload/v1599056071/hands-watch-ocean-sea-waves_oxugui.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://res.cloudinary.com/micahredding/image/upload/v1599056071/hands-watch-ocean-sea-waves_oxugui.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Resurrection is Participatory</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/the-resurrection-is-participatory/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Resurrection is Participatory" /><published>2019-03-28T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-03-28T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/the-resurrection-is-participatory</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/the-resurrection-is-participatory/"><![CDATA[<p>In my previous essay, <a href="http://micahredding.com/blog/the-resurrection-is-technological">The Resurrection is Technological</a>, I explored Paul’s argument in 1 Corinthians 15, that the resurrection is about God’s intention for humanity to reign over the cosmos.</p>

<p>According to Paul, God’s plan was for humans to rule the universe, and if humans failed to do so, God would not abandon his plan, but would <em>become human</em> to insure its completion. This is the reason for the incarnation.</p>

<p>For Paul, Death is the ultimate obstacle to humanity’s God-intended reign. And because God had ordained for humanity to reign over the universe, humanity would have to defeat death. This is the reason for the resurrection.</p>

<p>Thus, as Paul sees it, the resurrection is not simply an isolated future event. It is virtually synonymous with the unfolding reign of Christ, stretching from Christ’s own individual resurrection, up through the final defeat of death itself.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>For he must reign until he has put all his enemies under his feet. The last enemy to be destroyed is death. (1 Corinthians 15:24-26)</p>
</blockquote>

<p>In the previous essay, I emphasized that this reign is <em>participatory</em>. Christ does not come to remove humanity’s God-ordained reign, but to restore it, embody it, and invite us into it.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>…if we endure, we will also reign with him. (2 Timothy 2:12)</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This is the whole point of the New Testament. Christ never intended to reign alone. Christ’s triumph was in “bringing many sons and daughters to glory” (Hebrews 2:10). Christ’s glory is that others will be transformed to be like him (Romans 8:29). Christ’s reign is a reign we are called to participate in at all levels, even up to and including the apocalypse itself (1 Corinthians 6:3; Revelation 2:26-27; Revelation 20:4).</p>

<p>“Don’t you know that we will judge angels?”, Paul exclaims in 1 Corinthians 6:3.</p>

<p>This participatory reign of Christ wasn’t merely metaphorical. Paul expected his hearers to reign over cosmic beings, and they needed to be practicing for the occasion.</p>

<p>And indeed, resurrection is something Christ invites his followers to practice.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Heal the sick, raise the dead, cleanse those who have leprosy, drive out demons. Freely you have received; freely give. (Matthew 10:8)</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Jesus raised several people from the dead in his ministry, and so did his disciples. But Jesus anticipated that this would be even more dramatic in the future.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Very truly I tell you, whoever believes in me will do the works I have been doing, and they will do even greater things than these, because I am going to the Father. (John 14:12)</p>
</blockquote>

<p>So this is not something we wait around to do. This is something we participate in now, to the extent of our capabilities and gifts. We do it in healing, in caring, in feeding, in blessing. We do it in fighting for someone’s life, in searching for a cure, in seeking to understand the nature of life and death and disease.</p>

<p>We do it in remembering and celebrating and grieving.</p>

<p>Why must we play a part in this? Why can’t we simply wait for God to raise the dead, and set everything to rights? Why must we fight for our loved ones, and not simply wait for God to return them to us?</p>

<p>To understand that, we need to understand why death is so bad.</p>

<h2 id="death-is-a-tragedy-that-compounds">Death is a Tragedy that Compounds</h2>

<p>Death is a tragedy.</p>

<p>Anyone who tells you otherwise has either not experienced it up close and personally, or is trying to find a way of coming to terms with just how bad it is. It is a tragedy, not simply because someone is gone, but because all the relationships they were part of have now come to a halt.</p>

<p>What is the value of life, if not this? What is it we struggle for, fight for, and remember about someone, if not their relationships? What do we live to do?</p>

<p>We live to <em>be in relationship</em>—with people, animals, our bodies, the physical world.</p>

<p>Most of us want long, healthy, productive and meaningful lives. We want to contribute to others in our community, our society, our family. We want to create new things, and fix old things. We want to share joy and jokes and stories with other people, who will then share joy and jokes and stories with us.</p>

<p>Relationships, in the deepest sense, are who we are. We are not atomic, isolated, Cartesian minds—we are deeply intertwined networks of relationships, stretching out to the ends of the world.</p>

<p>Death takes all of this away.</p>

<p>Christians trust that the dead <a href="http://micahredding.com/blog/all-are-alive">still exist in some way</a>, and will exist in an even more robust way in the future. Many Christians don’t even think there is any subjective time between death, and the ultimate future that is waiting for us. Our loved ones may fall asleep, and wake up in a glorious world.</p>

<p>This might tempt us to think that death is no big deal. If death can be overcome, why mourn it at all? Why not rejoice in our loved one’s short-cut into glorious life?</p>

<p>This misses something significant.</p>

<p><strong>Death is a tragedy that compounds.</strong></p>

<p>Relationships compound. The experience you had with someone twenty years ago forms the bedrock of your experience today. If you lived or worked with someone for any significant amount of time, the relationship at the end of that process is inescapably unique. There’s no way to “make up for lost time” in a relationship—the relationship is simply different than it would have been otherwise.</p>

<p>So when someone dies, all the relationships they would have been part of are irrevocably changed.</p>

<p>All the lives they could have touched, good they could have done, grandchildren they could have seen, enemies they could have reconciled with, memories they could have made, conversations they could have had…</p>

<p>All of this is gone.</p>

<p>That loss grows with each passing day, impacting vast numbers of people, draining increasing amounts of potential good from the world.</p>

<p>There’s no obvious way to make up for not having a parent growing up, or not having your partner through the most exciting years of your life. There’s no way to make up for missing hundreds of conversations with your dad or your mom—or your sister, brother, or child. All of that has simply disappeared, and you grow into a different person than you would have been.</p>

<p>There’s no way to go back. This means that:</p>

<p><strong>Death never ceases to be a tragedy.</strong></p>

<p>Even if someone is resurrected, we will have lost immeasurable opportunities in between. Even in bringing someone back, we may never catch up with the positive impact they could have had.</p>

<p>If God were to resurrect everyone today, it would be a wonderful, amazing thing. It would be an incredible blessing. But it would not make up for the opportunities and relationships we have missed out on. It would not make up for what we have lost.</p>

<p>So if the real tragedy of death is to be overcome, perhaps there is something else that has to happen.</p>

<h2 id="why-the-resurrection-demands-participation">Why the Resurrection Demands Participation</h2>

<p>What could possibly make up for irreversible loss?</p>

<p>The only thing I can imagine making up for the loss of relationship—is if that loss catalyzed us to become capable of deeper, broader, and fuller relationship.</p>

<p>If loss gave us the opportunity to develop a deeper and fuller capacity for love than we could offer otherwise, then our reunion with our loved ones might not simply allow us to pick up where we left off, but might allow us to rejoin them in a much more profound way.</p>

<p>To put it in crude, numeric terms, imagine becoming capable of offering 1,000 years worth of relationship in the space of a year.</p>

<p>How might loss provide us with that opportunity? What might happen in the wake of a loss, that would help us grow in this way?</p>

<p>I want to suggest that it is our very commitment to participate in the resurrection—our commitment to grieve, heal, renew, work, and hope—that provides us with the opportunity to grow into the kind of people who can love in a much deeper and fuller form.</p>

<p><strong>After all, this is exactly what Christianity suggests: we must be conformed to the image of Christ. In some form or fashion, we must die and be raised. And in some form or fashion, we must raise the dead.</strong></p>

<p>Only in becoming the image of Christ, can we grow into the fullness of what we are intended to be. Only in becoming the image of Christ, can our love become like God’s love, reaching out to encompass the world.</p>

<p>And only that kind of capacity for love can make up for the irreversible tragedy that is death.</p>

<h2 id="how-we-participate-in-the-resurrection-of-the-dead">How we Participate in the Resurrection of the Dead</h2>

<p>I’ve been suggesting that biblically, defeating death is a process that is virtually synonymous with the unfolding reign of Christ. It’s something we participate in in all kinds of ways, and no aspect of human life is left out.</p>

<p>Everything from eating soup, to photographing the cosmos, ultimately plays a part, becoming an aspect of our living sacrifice. Every time we choose good over evil, or mercy over judgment, we are playing a role in the resurrection of the dead.</p>

<p>But if the tragedy of death is to be overcome, there must be specific things that only happen in the wake of someone’s death. There must be specific things that happen when we lose someone—things that help us grow in the ways we’ve been talking about, and help us strengthen our relationship with the person we’ve lost.</p>

<p>The first one, of course, is grief.</p>

<h3 id="blessed-are-those-who-mourn">Blessed are those who mourn</h3>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Blessed are those who mourn…” (Matthew 5:4)</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This verse used to perplex me. Why is it good to mourn? Are we supposed to be wishing for bad things to happen?</p>

<p>Having experienced a number of tragedies, I now realize that the answer is no. Bad things have <em>already</em> happened—the only question is how we are to respond. In the face of tragedy, we face two temptations:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>To decide that life is not worth living, that nothing matters, that all is lost, to resign ourselves to nothingness, and embrace unconscious nihilism. Or,</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>To insist that everything is okay, that nothing is as bad as it seems, that this is “just the natural order”, that “everything is for the best”.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>Both of these are ways of rejecting reality. One refuses to live in a reality this tragic, the other refuses to believe that reality is as tragic as it actually is.</p>

<p>Grief refuses to accept either of these answers.</p>

<p>The one who mourns is the one who sees the evil that has happened, and rather than drawing back from it, or pretending it’s alright—recognizes it for the horror it really is. And thus, they mourn.</p>

<p>Grief is the simultaneous recognition of the world as it is, and the world as it should be—and the recognition that these are not the same. Grief will bear no trite comfort, no “it’s for the best”, no “this is just the natural order”. Grief is the intense and insistent embrace of reality.</p>

<p>When we grieve, we hold together two impossible things: a love for the world, and a refusal to be okay with its horror. Grief exercises the ultimate existential muscle, helping us become stronger and more expansive, capable of experiencing deeper feeling and love—allowing us to share in God’s own perspective.</p>

<p>Grief is the heart of change. Grief is the soul of revolution. Grief provokes action—if the world is not as it should be, we must change the world.</p>

<p>Blessed are those who mourn, because those who mourn can be comforted. And those who grieve can be filled.</p>

<p>The world as it is, and the world as it should be, are poles apart. The ones who see this, and rather than accepting it, choose to participate in the solution—must always mourn.</p>

<h3 id="weep-with-those-who-weep">Weep with those who weep</h3>

<p>In the wake of tragedy, families and communities often come together. Relationships are strengthened around the loss they have experienced.</p>

<p>Relatives who have not talked in years may reunite, friends from different parts of the deceased’s life may connect. People who offer to help out may find themselves drawn into deep relationships with people they might not otherwise have ever talked to.</p>

<p>We may discover deep reserves in our friends and family that we never knew were there. We may discover new things about ourselves.</p>

<p>In all of this—in grieving someone, and in strengthening our relationships in their absence—we are creating a stronger and more definite relationship with the person we have lost.</p>

<p>In grief, we focus our thoughts and memories, we take stock of a person’s impact on the world, we realize they reached far beyond what we might assume. We collect and retell stories about them, we assess and evaluate their impact, we bring together different aspects of their life into a more cohesive picture.</p>

<p>We may find ourselves doing things that appear irrational. We may keep things that belonged to them, we may find ways to integrate them into new traditions and experiences, we may talk about what they would have wanted, we may visit their grave and speak to them about what is going on.</p>

<p>Much of this may not make sense, under the assumption that the deceased person is truly gone. But if we believe that the person still exists in some way, and will exist in a more robust way in the future—then we are still in a relationship with them.</p>

<p>And these things are our way of maintaining and strengthening that relationship.</p>

<h3 id="hope--act">Hope &amp; Act</h3>

<p>In John’s account of the resurrection of Lazarus, Jesus goes through each of these steps.</p>

<p>He weeps, expressing deep grief over the loss that has occurred.
He connects with the family and community, strengthening their relationship.
He remembers, strengthening his relationship with Lazarus himself.</p>

<p>In a moving part of the account, Jesus speaks with Lazarus’ sister Martha, asking her if she believes that Lazarus can be raised. <em>I know he will be raised at the end of time</em>, she responds.</p>

<p>But Jesus is not content with this. He wants Martha to see that the resurrection is not just something that happens eventually. The resurrection is already at work. It is in their midst. It is standing right in front of her.</p>

<p>Martha sees. And when she does, she has the stone rolled away. And then Jesus calls Lazarus to come out.</p>

<p>We might think that if Jesus could call forth Lazarus, that he could handle the stone. We might think that Jesus could have skipped the conversation, and just compelled Martha’s faith by moving straight to Lazarus’ resurrection.</p>

<p>But this is not how Jesus works.</p>

<p>Even in this extreme case, the resurrection is participatory. Martha must have faith that the resurrection is already at work. Then she must take the initiative to roll back the stone.</p>

<p>Only then can her voice join with Jesus, calling Lazarus to come forth.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>In the biblical story, God insists on performing the resurrection through humanity—even becoming human in Christ, in order to insure that this is how it would be accomplished. And according to the scriptures, Christ, as the ultimate human, has been given all power and authority to bring the resurrection about.</p>

<p>And yet, he does not do so immediately. The earliest Christians assumed that the ultimate resurrection would come soon, but they did not expect it to be immediate. Paul portrays the resurrection as an unfolding process, in which Christ subdues his enemies gradually.</p>

<p>Why? What is he waiting for?</p>

<p>Perhaps he is waiting for <em>us</em>. Perhaps participation is intrinsic to the process in a deeper way than we typically think. Perhaps this is shouted from the pages of the New Testament—and we haven’t been paying attention.</p>

<p>Perhaps only by grieving, weeping, comforting, remembering, trusting, and acting can we truly become the image of Christ—the kind of people we need to be, in order for the tragedy of death to be overcome.</p>

<p>After all, anything less would fall short of the Glory of Christ—because in Christ, <em>everything</em> is participatory.</p>]]></content><author><name>Micah Redding</name></author><category term="Theology" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In my previous essay, The Resurrection is Technological, I explored Paul’s argument in 1 Corinthians 15, that the resurrection is about God’s intention for humanity to reign over the cosmos. According to Paul, God’s plan was for humans to rule the universe, and if humans failed to do so, God would not abandon his plan, but would become human to insure its completion. This is the reason for the incarnation. For Paul, Death is the ultimate obstacle to humanity’s God-intended reign. And because God had ordained for humanity to reign over the universe, humanity would have to defeat death. This is the reason for the resurrection. Thus, as Paul sees it, the resurrection is not simply an isolated future event. It is virtually synonymous with the unfolding reign of Christ, stretching from Christ’s own individual resurrection, up through the final defeat of death itself. For he must reign until he has put all his enemies under his feet. The last enemy to be destroyed is death. (1 Corinthians 15:24-26) In the previous essay, I emphasized that this reign is participatory. Christ does not come to remove humanity’s God-ordained reign, but to restore it, embody it, and invite us into it. …if we endure, we will also reign with him. (2 Timothy 2:12) This is the whole point of the New Testament. Christ never intended to reign alone. Christ’s triumph was in “bringing many sons and daughters to glory” (Hebrews 2:10). Christ’s glory is that others will be transformed to be like him (Romans 8:29). Christ’s reign is a reign we are called to participate in at all levels, even up to and including the apocalypse itself (1 Corinthians 6:3; Revelation 2:26-27; Revelation 20:4). “Don’t you know that we will judge angels?”, Paul exclaims in 1 Corinthians 6:3. This participatory reign of Christ wasn’t merely metaphorical. Paul expected his hearers to reign over cosmic beings, and they needed to be practicing for the occasion. And indeed, resurrection is something Christ invites his followers to practice. Heal the sick, raise the dead, cleanse those who have leprosy, drive out demons. Freely you have received; freely give. (Matthew 10:8) Jesus raised several people from the dead in his ministry, and so did his disciples. But Jesus anticipated that this would be even more dramatic in the future. Very truly I tell you, whoever believes in me will do the works I have been doing, and they will do even greater things than these, because I am going to the Father. (John 14:12) So this is not something we wait around to do. This is something we participate in now, to the extent of our capabilities and gifts. We do it in healing, in caring, in feeding, in blessing. We do it in fighting for someone’s life, in searching for a cure, in seeking to understand the nature of life and death and disease. We do it in remembering and celebrating and grieving. Why must we play a part in this? Why can’t we simply wait for God to raise the dead, and set everything to rights? Why must we fight for our loved ones, and not simply wait for God to return them to us? To understand that, we need to understand why death is so bad. Death is a Tragedy that Compounds Death is a tragedy. Anyone who tells you otherwise has either not experienced it up close and personally, or is trying to find a way of coming to terms with just how bad it is. It is a tragedy, not simply because someone is gone, but because all the relationships they were part of have now come to a halt. What is the value of life, if not this? What is it we struggle for, fight for, and remember about someone, if not their relationships? What do we live to do? We live to be in relationship—with people, animals, our bodies, the physical world. Most of us want long, healthy, productive and meaningful lives. We want to contribute to others in our community, our society, our family. We want to create new things, and fix old things. We want to share joy and jokes and stories with other people, who will then share joy and jokes and stories with us. Relationships, in the deepest sense, are who we are. We are not atomic, isolated, Cartesian minds—we are deeply intertwined networks of relationships, stretching out to the ends of the world. Death takes all of this away. Christians trust that the dead still exist in some way, and will exist in an even more robust way in the future. Many Christians don’t even think there is any subjective time between death, and the ultimate future that is waiting for us. Our loved ones may fall asleep, and wake up in a glorious world. This might tempt us to think that death is no big deal. If death can be overcome, why mourn it at all? Why not rejoice in our loved one’s short-cut into glorious life? This misses something significant. Death is a tragedy that compounds. Relationships compound. The experience you had with someone twenty years ago forms the bedrock of your experience today. If you lived or worked with someone for any significant amount of time, the relationship at the end of that process is inescapably unique. There’s no way to “make up for lost time” in a relationship—the relationship is simply different than it would have been otherwise. So when someone dies, all the relationships they would have been part of are irrevocably changed. All the lives they could have touched, good they could have done, grandchildren they could have seen, enemies they could have reconciled with, memories they could have made, conversations they could have had… All of this is gone. That loss grows with each passing day, impacting vast numbers of people, draining increasing amounts of potential good from the world. There’s no obvious way to make up for not having a parent growing up, or not having your partner through the most exciting years of your life. There’s no way to make up for missing hundreds of conversations with your dad or your mom—or your sister, brother, or child. All of that has simply disappeared, and you grow into a different person than you would have been. There’s no way to go back. This means that: Death never ceases to be a tragedy. Even if someone is resurrected, we will have lost immeasurable opportunities in between. Even in bringing someone back, we may never catch up with the positive impact they could have had. If God were to resurrect everyone today, it would be a wonderful, amazing thing. It would be an incredible blessing. But it would not make up for the opportunities and relationships we have missed out on. It would not make up for what we have lost. So if the real tragedy of death is to be overcome, perhaps there is something else that has to happen. Why the Resurrection Demands Participation What could possibly make up for irreversible loss? The only thing I can imagine making up for the loss of relationship—is if that loss catalyzed us to become capable of deeper, broader, and fuller relationship. If loss gave us the opportunity to develop a deeper and fuller capacity for love than we could offer otherwise, then our reunion with our loved ones might not simply allow us to pick up where we left off, but might allow us to rejoin them in a much more profound way. To put it in crude, numeric terms, imagine becoming capable of offering 1,000 years worth of relationship in the space of a year. How might loss provide us with that opportunity? What might happen in the wake of a loss, that would help us grow in this way? I want to suggest that it is our very commitment to participate in the resurrection—our commitment to grieve, heal, renew, work, and hope—that provides us with the opportunity to grow into the kind of people who can love in a much deeper and fuller form. After all, this is exactly what Christianity suggests: we must be conformed to the image of Christ. In some form or fashion, we must die and be raised. And in some form or fashion, we must raise the dead. Only in becoming the image of Christ, can we grow into the fullness of what we are intended to be. Only in becoming the image of Christ, can our love become like God’s love, reaching out to encompass the world. And only that kind of capacity for love can make up for the irreversible tragedy that is death. How we Participate in the Resurrection of the Dead I’ve been suggesting that biblically, defeating death is a process that is virtually synonymous with the unfolding reign of Christ. It’s something we participate in in all kinds of ways, and no aspect of human life is left out. Everything from eating soup, to photographing the cosmos, ultimately plays a part, becoming an aspect of our living sacrifice. Every time we choose good over evil, or mercy over judgment, we are playing a role in the resurrection of the dead. But if the tragedy of death is to be overcome, there must be specific things that only happen in the wake of someone’s death. There must be specific things that happen when we lose someone—things that help us grow in the ways we’ve been talking about, and help us strengthen our relationship with the person we’ve lost. The first one, of course, is grief. Blessed are those who mourn “Blessed are those who mourn…” (Matthew 5:4) This verse used to perplex me. Why is it good to mourn? Are we supposed to be wishing for bad things to happen? Having experienced a number of tragedies, I now realize that the answer is no. Bad things have already happened—the only question is how we are to respond. In the face of tragedy, we face two temptations: To decide that life is not worth living, that nothing matters, that all is lost, to resign ourselves to nothingness, and embrace unconscious nihilism. Or, To insist that everything is okay, that nothing is as bad as it seems, that this is “just the natural order”, that “everything is for the best”. Both of these are ways of rejecting reality. One refuses to live in a reality this tragic, the other refuses to believe that reality is as tragic as it actually is. Grief refuses to accept either of these answers. The one who mourns is the one who sees the evil that has happened, and rather than drawing back from it, or pretending it’s alright—recognizes it for the horror it really is. And thus, they mourn. Grief is the simultaneous recognition of the world as it is, and the world as it should be—and the recognition that these are not the same. Grief will bear no trite comfort, no “it’s for the best”, no “this is just the natural order”. Grief is the intense and insistent embrace of reality. When we grieve, we hold together two impossible things: a love for the world, and a refusal to be okay with its horror. Grief exercises the ultimate existential muscle, helping us become stronger and more expansive, capable of experiencing deeper feeling and love—allowing us to share in God’s own perspective. Grief is the heart of change. Grief is the soul of revolution. Grief provokes action—if the world is not as it should be, we must change the world. Blessed are those who mourn, because those who mourn can be comforted. And those who grieve can be filled. The world as it is, and the world as it should be, are poles apart. The ones who see this, and rather than accepting it, choose to participate in the solution—must always mourn. Weep with those who weep In the wake of tragedy, families and communities often come together. Relationships are strengthened around the loss they have experienced. Relatives who have not talked in years may reunite, friends from different parts of the deceased’s life may connect. People who offer to help out may find themselves drawn into deep relationships with people they might not otherwise have ever talked to. We may discover deep reserves in our friends and family that we never knew were there. We may discover new things about ourselves. In all of this—in grieving someone, and in strengthening our relationships in their absence—we are creating a stronger and more definite relationship with the person we have lost. In grief, we focus our thoughts and memories, we take stock of a person’s impact on the world, we realize they reached far beyond what we might assume. We collect and retell stories about them, we assess and evaluate their impact, we bring together different aspects of their life into a more cohesive picture. We may find ourselves doing things that appear irrational. We may keep things that belonged to them, we may find ways to integrate them into new traditions and experiences, we may talk about what they would have wanted, we may visit their grave and speak to them about what is going on. Much of this may not make sense, under the assumption that the deceased person is truly gone. But if we believe that the person still exists in some way, and will exist in a more robust way in the future—then we are still in a relationship with them. And these things are our way of maintaining and strengthening that relationship. Hope &amp; Act In John’s account of the resurrection of Lazarus, Jesus goes through each of these steps. He weeps, expressing deep grief over the loss that has occurred. He connects with the family and community, strengthening their relationship. He remembers, strengthening his relationship with Lazarus himself. In a moving part of the account, Jesus speaks with Lazarus’ sister Martha, asking her if she believes that Lazarus can be raised. I know he will be raised at the end of time, she responds. But Jesus is not content with this. He wants Martha to see that the resurrection is not just something that happens eventually. The resurrection is already at work. It is in their midst. It is standing right in front of her. Martha sees. And when she does, she has the stone rolled away. And then Jesus calls Lazarus to come out. We might think that if Jesus could call forth Lazarus, that he could handle the stone. We might think that Jesus could have skipped the conversation, and just compelled Martha’s faith by moving straight to Lazarus’ resurrection. But this is not how Jesus works. Even in this extreme case, the resurrection is participatory. Martha must have faith that the resurrection is already at work. Then she must take the initiative to roll back the stone. Only then can her voice join with Jesus, calling Lazarus to come forth. Conclusion In the biblical story, God insists on performing the resurrection through humanity—even becoming human in Christ, in order to insure that this is how it would be accomplished. And according to the scriptures, Christ, as the ultimate human, has been given all power and authority to bring the resurrection about. And yet, he does not do so immediately. The earliest Christians assumed that the ultimate resurrection would come soon, but they did not expect it to be immediate. Paul portrays the resurrection as an unfolding process, in which Christ subdues his enemies gradually. Why? What is he waiting for? Perhaps he is waiting for us. Perhaps participation is intrinsic to the process in a deeper way than we typically think. Perhaps this is shouted from the pages of the New Testament—and we haven’t been paying attention. Perhaps only by grieving, weeping, comforting, remembering, trusting, and acting can we truly become the image of Christ—the kind of people we need to be, in order for the tragedy of death to be overcome. After all, anything less would fall short of the Glory of Christ—because in Christ, everything is participatory.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://res.cloudinary.com/micahredding/image/upload/v1553806943/htwoj8lrktnvumvyhzbb.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://res.cloudinary.com/micahredding/image/upload/v1553806943/htwoj8lrktnvumvyhzbb.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Kingdom of God has a biotechnological research agenda</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/the-kingdom-of-god-has-a-biotechnological-research-agenda/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Kingdom of God has a biotechnological research agenda" /><published>2019-03-13T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-03-13T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/the-kingdom-of-god-has-a-biotechnological-research-agenda</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/the-kingdom-of-god-has-a-biotechnological-research-agenda/"><![CDATA[<p>The Kingdom of God has a biotechnological research agenda.</p>

<p>We must cultivate all life, starting from the bottom up. We must learn how life works, how evolution unfolds, how ecosystems function—and we must learn to bless and uplift those processes into glorious flourishing.</p>

<p>This is the creative process that God models for us in Genesis 1—and then immediately calls us into. This is what causes Paul to exclaim:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“All creation waits in eager expectation for the children of God to be revealed…in hopes that creation itself will be liberated to join in the freedom and the glory of the children of God!” (Romans 8:19-21)</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This is what leads to Revelation’s vision of a city so big it can encompass the entire world, so powerful it reaches beyond the stratosphere, and so glorious it pours life and healing into all creation.</p>

<p>To do this, we must pour intense research into the fundamentals of life: genetics and cellular structure—epigenetics, metabolism, and intracellular programming—ecosystems, biogenesis, and evolutionary development. We must learn to create, edit, and manage these systems, to resurrect extinct species, give existing species new life, and protect endangered species from extinction.</p>

<p>We must not return to a prior ecological state, or be content with simply limiting environmental damage. We must move aggressively forward into an ecosystem that is thriving like never before.</p>

<p>And if we do so, then <em>we</em> will thrive like never before. Not only will we unleash unimaginable global flourishing, we will create a civilization rich beyond its wildest dreams. We will learn to cure disease, to extend life, to grow better food, to need fewer resources, to construct vibrant new ecosystems on other planets.</p>

<p>We will learn to optimize the earth for maximum biodiversity—until our oceans are teeming with vast creatures of the deep, our skies are full of glorious life and color, and our plains are bringing forth vegetation that would make Eden weep.</p>

<p>Our wilds will be full of large creatures, beasts of massive grace and beauty, animals whose names our ancestors first whispered in awe. Our cities will be refreshing beacons of light, skyscrapers literally reaching the skies—not enclosing us in concrete and steel, but raining down nourishment, greenery, and life.</p>

<p>This is the calling of God. It’s what we were uniquely made to do. And it is precisely that which most reflects the one whose image we are. It’s a calling described over and over in the biblical story, from Genesis to Revelation, from Old Testament to New Testament, from first creation to new creation.</p>

<p>It’s the mission without which all life will perish. It’s the mission without which we will be purposeless and lost. It’s the mission without which humanity will not prosper.</p>

<p>And it’s the mission that contains everything our creator promised us, on the first day we walked with God in this beautiful, glorious creation.</p>]]></content><author><name>Micah Redding</name></author><category term="Transhuman" /><category term="Christian Transhumanism" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Kingdom of God has a biotechnological research agenda. We must cultivate all life, starting from the bottom up. We must learn how life works, how evolution unfolds, how ecosystems function—and we must learn to bless and uplift those processes into glorious flourishing. This is the creative process that God models for us in Genesis 1—and then immediately calls us into. This is what causes Paul to exclaim: “All creation waits in eager expectation for the children of God to be revealed…in hopes that creation itself will be liberated to join in the freedom and the glory of the children of God!” (Romans 8:19-21) This is what leads to Revelation’s vision of a city so big it can encompass the entire world, so powerful it reaches beyond the stratosphere, and so glorious it pours life and healing into all creation. To do this, we must pour intense research into the fundamentals of life: genetics and cellular structure—epigenetics, metabolism, and intracellular programming—ecosystems, biogenesis, and evolutionary development. We must learn to create, edit, and manage these systems, to resurrect extinct species, give existing species new life, and protect endangered species from extinction. We must not return to a prior ecological state, or be content with simply limiting environmental damage. We must move aggressively forward into an ecosystem that is thriving like never before. And if we do so, then we will thrive like never before. Not only will we unleash unimaginable global flourishing, we will create a civilization rich beyond its wildest dreams. We will learn to cure disease, to extend life, to grow better food, to need fewer resources, to construct vibrant new ecosystems on other planets. We will learn to optimize the earth for maximum biodiversity—until our oceans are teeming with vast creatures of the deep, our skies are full of glorious life and color, and our plains are bringing forth vegetation that would make Eden weep. Our wilds will be full of large creatures, beasts of massive grace and beauty, animals whose names our ancestors first whispered in awe. Our cities will be refreshing beacons of light, skyscrapers literally reaching the skies—not enclosing us in concrete and steel, but raining down nourishment, greenery, and life. This is the calling of God. It’s what we were uniquely made to do. And it is precisely that which most reflects the one whose image we are. It’s a calling described over and over in the biblical story, from Genesis to Revelation, from Old Testament to New Testament, from first creation to new creation. It’s the mission without which all life will perish. It’s the mission without which we will be purposeless and lost. It’s the mission without which humanity will not prosper. And it’s the mission that contains everything our creator promised us, on the first day we walked with God in this beautiful, glorious creation.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://res.cloudinary.com/micahredding/image/upload/v1552514863/usxowj7y3pbng4t0thli.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://res.cloudinary.com/micahredding/image/upload/v1552514863/usxowj7y3pbng4t0thli.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Miracles vs Magic</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/miracles-vs-magic/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Miracles vs Magic" /><published>2018-12-04T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2018-12-04T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/miracles-vs-magic</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/miracles-vs-magic/"><![CDATA[<p>In 1600, during Giordano Bruno’s heresy trial, the inquisitors asked a question: <em>Did he believe Jesus’ miracles were performed by magic?</em></p>

<p>It’s hard for us to understand the significance of this question. In our post-Enlightenment world, this seems like a distinction without a difference, bordering on the absurd.</p>

<p>And yet this miracle / magic distinction runs quite deep. Sociologists suggest that this division is a distinctive aspect of monotheism. So what does it mean, and how does it connect to our world today?</p>

<h2 id="jesus-on-miracles">Jesus on Miracles</h2>

<p>In Christianity, <a href="http://micahredding.com/blog/christianity-is-love">everything is relational</a>. So in the Gospels, the distinction between miracles and magic is that miracles are manifestations of legitimate pro-social authority, while magic is a manifestation of anti-social control.</p>

<p>When Jesus heals people, for example, he often tells them that they have healed themselves. “Your faith has made you well.” But in turn, he asserts that “My sheep hear my voice”. In other words, Jesus is not healing by exercising control over the people who come to him. Rather, he is commanding them to be healed, and in recognition of his spiritual authority, they are obediently healing themselves.</p>

<p>This response validates Jesus’ claims to spiritual authority. The community is responding to Jesus’ call for healing, affirming his authority in the process.</p>

<p>I’ve argued elsewhere that <a href="http://micahredding.com/blog/wireheading-faith-healing-and-the-placebo-effect">this is how the placebo effect operates</a>. The placebo effect is the most documented phenomenon in medical history, and contrary to popular interpretation, it points to the pervasive ability of people to heal themselves.</p>

<p>We needn’t make any assumptions about how this works. Materialistically, spiritually, or some combination of the two—the phenomenon is the same. People have a widely documented capacity for self-healing.</p>

<p>Why, then, don’t people just spontaneously heal themselves as soon as symptoms start to manifest? Why wait until someone gives them a placebo?</p>

<p>My argument is that this self-healing ability is fundamentally dangerous. Just as pharmacists don’t dispense narcotics without a prescription, your brain requires external authorization in order to engage its most extreme functions.</p>

<p>For your own protection, you cannot invoke your own abilities without permission from a legitimate authority.</p>

<p>If this is true, it means that at a deep level, your brain possesses the ability to recognize legitimate, pro-social sources of authority. And it means that this system <em>necessarily supercedes the conscious, volitional mind</em>.</p>

<p>Your brain can recognize legitimate authority, whether you realize it or not.</p>

<p>When a Doctor, Priest, or Rabbi blesses you and tells you to get well, this internal system may recognize the presence of a legitimate pro-social authority, and unlock various mental and physical resources.</p>

<p>Like everything else, this system will be imperfect. But given its importance, it’s also likely to be one of the more robust systems in the human brain. This system likely grants varying levels of access, to varying kinds of abilities, depending on the nature of the authority.</p>

<p>This means that <strong><em>healings are evidence of legitimate pro-social authority</em></strong>.</p>

<p>This is what the Gospels suggest.</p>

<p>The Gospels continually present Jesus’ widespread, phenomenal healings as evidence of Jesus’ spiritual authority. Jesus always claims to be operating on the spiritual authority of God, as validated <em>through</em> the community, <em>by</em> the healings.</p>

<p>That’s the biblical understanding of a miracle. So what is magic?</p>

<h2 id="jesus-on-trial-for-magic">Jesus on Trial for Magic</h2>

<p>From the earliest times, skeptics have claimed that Jesus’ miracles were done by magic. In fact, this claim shows up in the Gospels themselves—as his opponents assert that Jesus healed people through the power of demons.</p>

<p>It’s important to understand the distinction here. To claim that these healings were <em>magic</em> was to claim that Jesus wasn’t legitimately recognized by the community, but was instead entering into a pact with spiritual forces which were opposed to the community.</p>

<p>If that’s what Jesus was doing, then the healings weren’t evidence of spiritual authority at all, but were evidence of having claimed spiritual authority on false pretenses. Further, they were evidence that Jesus was using these healings to undermine the community’s very existence.</p>

<p>So this was a very significant charge. Jesus answers this charge in two slightly different ways.</p>

<p>First, <strong>How can an anti-social force do pro-social things?</strong></p>

<p>If the community is being healed, set right, and made well, how can that be a force working against the community? With enemies like these—who needs friends! More to the point, if this was a destructive force, it was the most ineffective one in history.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“If by the Prince of Demons, I cast out demons, how can his kingdom stand?”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Second, <strong>If you reject this evidence of spiritual authority, what further evidence is left?</strong></p>

<p>This is Jesus’ infamous “unpardonable sin” passage. Jesus tells his opponents that it is understandable to have doubted God (who you cannot see), or himself (who was unexpected). But if you look at the only evidence that could be provided, and choose to dismiss it—what else is left?</p>

<p>What further proof could you find? What else could God or the community do? What could possibly keep you from sliding into nihilism?</p>

<p>If you interpret the <em>flourishing of the community</em> as a sign of the <em>destruction of the community</em>, then what kind of flourishing have you left open to yourself?</p>

<h2 id="the-key-to-the-case">The Key to the Case</h2>

<p>So this is the question: Does Jesus heal by miracles, or by magic? Does Jesus heal by the pro-social, emergent recognition of his spiritual authority within the community—or by the anti-social exercise of illegitimate control?</p>

<p>Key to the case is something that we tend to ignore, but the Gospels go out of their way to point out:</p>

<p><em>Jesus couldn’t heal everyone.</em></p>

<p>There were particular places, such as his own hometown, where Jesus was not able to heal people. The Gospels explain that this was because they were not receptive to his spiritual authority. In other words, having dismissed him as a mere carpenter’s son, Jesus’ power was nullified.</p>

<p>For many Christians, this is a point of embarrassment. How could the power of the Son of God fail? But for the Gospels, <em>this is key.</em></p>

<p>If Jesus was exercising illegitimate control, cooperating with an anti-community force, he could coerce anyone and everyone to be healed.</p>

<p>But if Jesus was <em>authorizing</em> people to be healed, and their deepest selves were freely responding to his command, then it was a true recognition of pro-social authority. It validated the fact that God—the ultimate pro-social force—was really at work.</p>

<p>And it meant that sometimes, <em>Jesus’ healings had to fail</em>. God does not coerce anyone’s allegiance, and so the Son of God cannot coerce anyone’s self-healing.</p>

<p>It’s important to note that the Gospels don’t stop with the physical healings. Jesus goes on from healing people, to feeding crowds, to walking across water and calming a storm.</p>

<p>But the Gospels present all of these as the exercise of authority. Jesus commands the storm to be still, and it does. The Son of Man has authority even over the Sea.</p>

<p>This authority is remarkable precisely because it is not coercive power. In the worldview of the Gospels, we must conclude that the Sea had some measure of choice. Like a skilled horse-whisperer with an anxious animal, Jesus tells the Sea to be calm, and it responds in recognition of someone who can be trusted.</p>

<p>So these are the possibilities. One—that Jesus worked through the exercise of pro-social, legitimate and cooperative authority. Another—that Jesus worked through the exercise of anti-social, illegitimate control.</p>

<p>These possibilities have been debated since the earliest times.</p>

<p>But this is the difference between miracles and magic.</p>]]></content><author><name>Micah Redding</name></author><category term="Theology" /><category term="Christian Transhumanism" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In 1600, during Giordano Bruno’s heresy trial, the inquisitors asked a question: Did he believe Jesus’ miracles were performed by magic? It’s hard for us to understand the significance of this question. In our post-Enlightenment world, this seems like a distinction without a difference, bordering on the absurd. And yet this miracle / magic distinction runs quite deep. Sociologists suggest that this division is a distinctive aspect of monotheism. So what does it mean, and how does it connect to our world today? Jesus on Miracles In Christianity, everything is relational. So in the Gospels, the distinction between miracles and magic is that miracles are manifestations of legitimate pro-social authority, while magic is a manifestation of anti-social control. When Jesus heals people, for example, he often tells them that they have healed themselves. “Your faith has made you well.” But in turn, he asserts that “My sheep hear my voice”. In other words, Jesus is not healing by exercising control over the people who come to him. Rather, he is commanding them to be healed, and in recognition of his spiritual authority, they are obediently healing themselves. This response validates Jesus’ claims to spiritual authority. The community is responding to Jesus’ call for healing, affirming his authority in the process. I’ve argued elsewhere that this is how the placebo effect operates. The placebo effect is the most documented phenomenon in medical history, and contrary to popular interpretation, it points to the pervasive ability of people to heal themselves. We needn’t make any assumptions about how this works. Materialistically, spiritually, or some combination of the two—the phenomenon is the same. People have a widely documented capacity for self-healing. Why, then, don’t people just spontaneously heal themselves as soon as symptoms start to manifest? Why wait until someone gives them a placebo? My argument is that this self-healing ability is fundamentally dangerous. Just as pharmacists don’t dispense narcotics without a prescription, your brain requires external authorization in order to engage its most extreme functions. For your own protection, you cannot invoke your own abilities without permission from a legitimate authority. If this is true, it means that at a deep level, your brain possesses the ability to recognize legitimate, pro-social sources of authority. And it means that this system necessarily supercedes the conscious, volitional mind. Your brain can recognize legitimate authority, whether you realize it or not. When a Doctor, Priest, or Rabbi blesses you and tells you to get well, this internal system may recognize the presence of a legitimate pro-social authority, and unlock various mental and physical resources. Like everything else, this system will be imperfect. But given its importance, it’s also likely to be one of the more robust systems in the human brain. This system likely grants varying levels of access, to varying kinds of abilities, depending on the nature of the authority. This means that healings are evidence of legitimate pro-social authority. This is what the Gospels suggest. The Gospels continually present Jesus’ widespread, phenomenal healings as evidence of Jesus’ spiritual authority. Jesus always claims to be operating on the spiritual authority of God, as validated through the community, by the healings. That’s the biblical understanding of a miracle. So what is magic? Jesus on Trial for Magic From the earliest times, skeptics have claimed that Jesus’ miracles were done by magic. In fact, this claim shows up in the Gospels themselves—as his opponents assert that Jesus healed people through the power of demons. It’s important to understand the distinction here. To claim that these healings were magic was to claim that Jesus wasn’t legitimately recognized by the community, but was instead entering into a pact with spiritual forces which were opposed to the community. If that’s what Jesus was doing, then the healings weren’t evidence of spiritual authority at all, but were evidence of having claimed spiritual authority on false pretenses. Further, they were evidence that Jesus was using these healings to undermine the community’s very existence. So this was a very significant charge. Jesus answers this charge in two slightly different ways. First, How can an anti-social force do pro-social things? If the community is being healed, set right, and made well, how can that be a force working against the community? With enemies like these—who needs friends! More to the point, if this was a destructive force, it was the most ineffective one in history. “If by the Prince of Demons, I cast out demons, how can his kingdom stand?” Second, If you reject this evidence of spiritual authority, what further evidence is left? This is Jesus’ infamous “unpardonable sin” passage. Jesus tells his opponents that it is understandable to have doubted God (who you cannot see), or himself (who was unexpected). But if you look at the only evidence that could be provided, and choose to dismiss it—what else is left? What further proof could you find? What else could God or the community do? What could possibly keep you from sliding into nihilism? If you interpret the flourishing of the community as a sign of the destruction of the community, then what kind of flourishing have you left open to yourself? The Key to the Case So this is the question: Does Jesus heal by miracles, or by magic? Does Jesus heal by the pro-social, emergent recognition of his spiritual authority within the community—or by the anti-social exercise of illegitimate control? Key to the case is something that we tend to ignore, but the Gospels go out of their way to point out: Jesus couldn’t heal everyone. There were particular places, such as his own hometown, where Jesus was not able to heal people. The Gospels explain that this was because they were not receptive to his spiritual authority. In other words, having dismissed him as a mere carpenter’s son, Jesus’ power was nullified. For many Christians, this is a point of embarrassment. How could the power of the Son of God fail? But for the Gospels, this is key. If Jesus was exercising illegitimate control, cooperating with an anti-community force, he could coerce anyone and everyone to be healed. But if Jesus was authorizing people to be healed, and their deepest selves were freely responding to his command, then it was a true recognition of pro-social authority. It validated the fact that God—the ultimate pro-social force—was really at work. And it meant that sometimes, Jesus’ healings had to fail. God does not coerce anyone’s allegiance, and so the Son of God cannot coerce anyone’s self-healing. It’s important to note that the Gospels don’t stop with the physical healings. Jesus goes on from healing people, to feeding crowds, to walking across water and calming a storm. But the Gospels present all of these as the exercise of authority. Jesus commands the storm to be still, and it does. The Son of Man has authority even over the Sea. This authority is remarkable precisely because it is not coercive power. In the worldview of the Gospels, we must conclude that the Sea had some measure of choice. Like a skilled horse-whisperer with an anxious animal, Jesus tells the Sea to be calm, and it responds in recognition of someone who can be trusted. So these are the possibilities. One—that Jesus worked through the exercise of pro-social, legitimate and cooperative authority. Another—that Jesus worked through the exercise of anti-social, illegitimate control. These possibilities have been debated since the earliest times. But this is the difference between miracles and magic.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://res.cloudinary.com/micahredding/image/upload/v1543952473/z1mjapwacpgbs5baza4v.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://res.cloudinary.com/micahredding/image/upload/v1543952473/z1mjapwacpgbs5baza4v.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Dealing with Death</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/dealing-with-death/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dealing with Death" /><published>2018-05-30T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-05-30T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/dealing-with-death</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/dealing-with-death/"><![CDATA[<p>On Tuesday, April 24th, I was <a href="https://www.christiantranshumanism.org/blog/bbc-immortality-the-why-factor">interviewed on BBC Radio</a> about technology, the pursuit of immortality, and the meaning of death.</p>

<p>In the middle of that night, we were awakened by a call from an out-of-state hospital, telling us that my father-in-law had lost consciousness.</p>

<p>We spent the next week with doctors and nurses and members of the community, fighting for his life. On May 4th, around noon, he died peacefully, surrounded by friends and family.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.humans.family/patrick-hogan">People express their grief in many ways</a>—and I have grieved in many ways over these last few weeks. One way that I express it, though, is to try to put my thoughts in order, to try to capture what I am experiencing and processing.</p>

<p>These are some things I wrote during this process.</p>

<p>I think that all expressions of grief capture something that is true, and leave out something that is true—including this one.</p>

<p>Read it in that spirit.</p>

<hr />

<p>Death is bad.</p>

<p>Anyone who tells you otherwise has either not experienced it personally and individually, or is trying to find a way of coming to terms with just how bad it is.</p>

<p>It is a tragedy—a loss of so many, <em>many</em> irreplaceable things.</p>

<p>People who believe in an afterlife or a higher spiritual dimension might suggest that the person hasn’t really been lost at all. Why, therefore, should we cry? What has really been lost?</p>

<p>But something significant <em>has</em> been lost:</p>

<p>Relationships.</p>

<p>What really is the value of life, if not this? What is it we struggle for, fight for, and remember about someone, if not their relationships? What do we live to do?</p>

<p>We live to <em>be in relationship</em>—with people, animals, our bodies, the physical world.</p>

<p>Most of us want long, healthy, productive and meaningful lives. We want to contribute to others in our community, our society, our family. We want to create new things, and fix old things. We want to share joy and jokes and stories with other people, who will then share joy and jokes and stories with us.</p>

<p>Relationships, in the deepest sense, are who we are. We are not atomic, isolated, Cartesian minds—we are a deeply intertwined network of relationships, stretching out to the ends of the world.</p>

<p>Death takes all of this away.</p>

<p>I don’t want to mitigate this reality. I don’t want to hide from, or sugar-coat these facts. I want to know it and acknowledge it fully, for the all-embracing tragedy it is.</p>

<p>In that way, I know that whatever hope I find, and whatever goodness I discover, is no mere coping mechanism for hiding from the truth.</p>

<p>Whatever else I say, I want to know that it isn’t a shallow platitude, but something that can ring out through the halls of an ICU.</p>

<hr />

<p>I think there’s something good that happens when we grieve.</p>

<p>We focus our thoughts and memories, we take stock of a person’s impact on the world, we realize they reached far beyond what we might assume.</p>

<p>We think of all the things we wish we had done. We process all the missed opportunities. We celebrate them and mourn them and love them.</p>

<p>This is good, and I think that sometimes the goodness of it makes us think that death itself is desirable. Like maybe finitude is the value of life.</p>

<p>But that’s a mistake. This process of bringing good out of bad requires life. This is what life is—it’s what life does. The goodness contained in grief isn’t brought to us by death. It’s created by life.</p>

<p>Grief is a taste of resurrection. Life bringing life out of even death.</p>

<hr />

<p>Death is a tragedy. That’s the reality of it.</p>

<p>“Death is a doorway to a better life”
…or…
“Life is valuable because it is finite”</p>

<p>Are both ways of saying that death is not <em>really</em> a tragedy. But I would rather just face the tragedy head-on.</p>

<p>In a sense, my whole project is to figure out how <em>hope</em> can be real and meaningful, without ever backing away from the tragedy of our lived experience.</p>

<p>The resolution is to recognize that tragedy is real—but that tragedy can be ameliorated, and eventually, overcome. And what we learn through the tragedy can make the final outcome better than it would have been.</p>

<p>That’s redemption.</p>

<p>And it requires our participation. We have to recognize tragedy for the horror it is, grieve it, and learn from it. Only then can we participate with life in overcoming that tragedy.</p>

<p>But this is complicated. Thinking about death, the loss of someone is a tragedy, and it’s a tragedy that compounds. Even if they are resurrected, we will have lost immeasurable opportunities in between.</p>

<p>That might indicate that death can be overcome, but never ceases to be a tragedy.</p>

<p>Unless there’s something else.</p>

<p>Perhaps if we learn from their loss, then their resurrection can do more than simply undo the loss. Perhaps it can create new, better possibilities for that relationship. Perhaps we can all make better choices on the other side, than we ever would have otherwise.</p>

<p>If that’s a possibility, it’s one that requires us to be involved and engaged in learning from and seeking to overcome these tragedies.</p>

<p>And that’s why I never want to draw back from any of it.</p>

<p>Whatever the loss, I want to be there, in the flesh, experiencing that very real tragedy with all of my being.</p>]]></content><author><name>Micah Redding</name></author><category term="Human" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[On Tuesday, April 24th, I was interviewed on BBC Radio about technology, the pursuit of immortality, and the meaning of death. In the middle of that night, we were awakened by a call from an out-of-state hospital, telling us that my father-in-law had lost consciousness. We spent the next week with doctors and nurses and members of the community, fighting for his life. On May 4th, around noon, he died peacefully, surrounded by friends and family. People express their grief in many ways—and I have grieved in many ways over these last few weeks. One way that I express it, though, is to try to put my thoughts in order, to try to capture what I am experiencing and processing. These are some things I wrote during this process. I think that all expressions of grief capture something that is true, and leave out something that is true—including this one. Read it in that spirit. Death is bad. Anyone who tells you otherwise has either not experienced it personally and individually, or is trying to find a way of coming to terms with just how bad it is. It is a tragedy—a loss of so many, many irreplaceable things. People who believe in an afterlife or a higher spiritual dimension might suggest that the person hasn’t really been lost at all. Why, therefore, should we cry? What has really been lost? But something significant has been lost: Relationships. What really is the value of life, if not this? What is it we struggle for, fight for, and remember about someone, if not their relationships? What do we live to do? We live to be in relationship—with people, animals, our bodies, the physical world. Most of us want long, healthy, productive and meaningful lives. We want to contribute to others in our community, our society, our family. We want to create new things, and fix old things. We want to share joy and jokes and stories with other people, who will then share joy and jokes and stories with us. Relationships, in the deepest sense, are who we are. We are not atomic, isolated, Cartesian minds—we are a deeply intertwined network of relationships, stretching out to the ends of the world. Death takes all of this away. I don’t want to mitigate this reality. I don’t want to hide from, or sugar-coat these facts. I want to know it and acknowledge it fully, for the all-embracing tragedy it is. In that way, I know that whatever hope I find, and whatever goodness I discover, is no mere coping mechanism for hiding from the truth. Whatever else I say, I want to know that it isn’t a shallow platitude, but something that can ring out through the halls of an ICU. I think there’s something good that happens when we grieve. We focus our thoughts and memories, we take stock of a person’s impact on the world, we realize they reached far beyond what we might assume. We think of all the things we wish we had done. We process all the missed opportunities. We celebrate them and mourn them and love them. This is good, and I think that sometimes the goodness of it makes us think that death itself is desirable. Like maybe finitude is the value of life. But that’s a mistake. This process of bringing good out of bad requires life. This is what life is—it’s what life does. The goodness contained in grief isn’t brought to us by death. It’s created by life. Grief is a taste of resurrection. Life bringing life out of even death. Death is a tragedy. That’s the reality of it. “Death is a doorway to a better life” …or… “Life is valuable because it is finite” Are both ways of saying that death is not really a tragedy. But I would rather just face the tragedy head-on. In a sense, my whole project is to figure out how hope can be real and meaningful, without ever backing away from the tragedy of our lived experience. The resolution is to recognize that tragedy is real—but that tragedy can be ameliorated, and eventually, overcome. And what we learn through the tragedy can make the final outcome better than it would have been. That’s redemption. And it requires our participation. We have to recognize tragedy for the horror it is, grieve it, and learn from it. Only then can we participate with life in overcoming that tragedy. But this is complicated. Thinking about death, the loss of someone is a tragedy, and it’s a tragedy that compounds. Even if they are resurrected, we will have lost immeasurable opportunities in between. That might indicate that death can be overcome, but never ceases to be a tragedy. Unless there’s something else. Perhaps if we learn from their loss, then their resurrection can do more than simply undo the loss. Perhaps it can create new, better possibilities for that relationship. Perhaps we can all make better choices on the other side, than we ever would have otherwise. If that’s a possibility, it’s one that requires us to be involved and engaged in learning from and seeking to overcome these tragedies. And that’s why I never want to draw back from any of it. Whatever the loss, I want to be there, in the flesh, experiencing that very real tragedy with all of my being.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://res.cloudinary.com/micahredding/image/upload/v1527917254/vzxd3zsvjyickyw77quh.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://res.cloudinary.com/micahredding/image/upload/v1527917254/vzxd3zsvjyickyw77quh.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Be Thou My Vision, the Royal Wedding &amp;amp; Theosis</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/be-thou-my-vision-and-theosis/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Be Thou My Vision, the Royal Wedding &amp;amp; Theosis" /><published>2018-05-20T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-05-20T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/be-thou-my-vision-and-theosis</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/be-thou-my-vision-and-theosis/"><![CDATA[<p>At the Royal Wedding yesterday, there was a brief moment when everyone in attendance, including the royal couple, sang together. They were singing a melody shared by <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_VpSqAcLrDI&amp;index=36&amp;t=0s&amp;list=PL-S97LROgRNzo--DO8vVoRMQXFnBPYXXw">Be Thou My Vision</a>, one of the most beautiful hymns ever written. The hymn has origins deep in Irish history—perhaps even tracing back to Saint Patrick himself.</p>

<p>But what may be even more beautiful than the haunting Celtic melody, is the profound meaning of its lyrics. This song, more than any other I can think of, evokes the ancient Christian concept of <em>theosis</em>.</p>

<p><em>Theosis</em> literally means “divinization”. In Christian thought, it means becoming a “partaker of the divine nature” (2 Peter 1:4)—being united with God, such that God’s nature permeates and transforms your own.</p>

<p>This is what we enact in Communion or Eucharist, symbolically consuming Christ’s body and blood, that we may be transformed into Christ’s body and blood.</p>

<p>This is why Christ came, according to the church fathers. <em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Divinization_(Christian)#Patristic_writings">“God became what we are, that we might become what he is.”</a></em></p>

<p>One of the most poignant statements about this is in Paul’s second letter to the Corinthians:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>And we all, who with unveiled faces contemplate the Lord’s glory, are being transformed into his image with ever-increasing glory, which comes from the Lord, who is the Spirit. (2 Corinthians 3:18)</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The image is of vision—of seeing face to face. In ancient times, according to Paul, people had covered their faces when approaching God. They could not see him, could not understand him. There was no intimate relationship.</p>

<p>They longed to cross that chasm.</p>

<p><em><a href="http://micahredding.com/blog/my-grandfather">My eyes shall see him, mine and not another</a></em>, echo the heart-wrenching words of Job.</p>

<p>In the biblical story, humans were made in the image of God, made to reflect God’s glory to all creation. Thus, to see God dimly, through a covering, was to be disconnected from what we really are. It was to fall short of the glory of God.</p>

<p><em><a href="https://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=1+corinthians+13:12&amp;version=NIV">Now we see as in mirror—then we shall see face to face.</a></em></p>

<p>In Christ, according to Paul, that covering has been ripped away. Now, we can look at God face to face. Now, in contemplating God, we are transformed into a vision of God.</p>

<p>Every relationship transforms us. We become part of the other person, and they become part of us. We become increasingly like each other. The more clearly we see the other person, the more deeply they become part of who we are.</p>

<p>To see God face-to-face is to be in a relationship deeper and more intimate than you can imagine. It is to know that God is within you, transforming you into God’s image and glory.</p>

<p>The desire to look upon God, to have that relationship fill you and transform you in every way, to feel it as deep as love, and as strong as power—is what this song is about.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Be Thou my Vision, O Lord of my heart;<br />
Naught be all else to me, save that Thou art.<br />
Thou my best Thought, by day or by night,<br />
Waking or sleeping, Thy presence my light.</p>

  <p>Be Thou my Wisdom, and Thou my true Word;<br />
I ever with Thee and Thou with me, Lord;<br />
Thou my great Father, I Thy true son;<br />
Thou in me dwelling, and I with Thee one.</p>

  <p>Be Thou my battle Shield, Sword for the fight;<br />
Be Thou my Dignity, Thou my Delight;<br />
Thou my soul’s Shelter, Thou my high Tower:<br />
Raise Thou me heavenward, O Power of my power.</p>

  <p>Riches I heed not, nor man’s empty praise,<br />
Thou mine Inheritance, now and always:<br />
Thou and Thou only, first in my heart,<br />
High King of Heaven, my Treasure Thou art.</p>

  <p>High King of Heaven, my victory won,<br />
May I reach Heaven’s joys, O bright Heaven’s Sun!<br />
<em>Heart of my own heart</em>, whatever befall,<br />
Still be my Vision, O Ruler of all.</p>
</blockquote>]]></content><author><name>Micah Redding</name></author><category term="Theology" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[At the Royal Wedding yesterday, there was a brief moment when everyone in attendance, including the royal couple, sang together. They were singing a melody shared by Be Thou My Vision, one of the most beautiful hymns ever written. The hymn has origins deep in Irish history—perhaps even tracing back to Saint Patrick himself. But what may be even more beautiful than the haunting Celtic melody, is the profound meaning of its lyrics. This song, more than any other I can think of, evokes the ancient Christian concept of theosis. Theosis literally means “divinization”. In Christian thought, it means becoming a “partaker of the divine nature” (2 Peter 1:4)—being united with God, such that God’s nature permeates and transforms your own. This is what we enact in Communion or Eucharist, symbolically consuming Christ’s body and blood, that we may be transformed into Christ’s body and blood. This is why Christ came, according to the church fathers. “God became what we are, that we might become what he is.” One of the most poignant statements about this is in Paul’s second letter to the Corinthians: And we all, who with unveiled faces contemplate the Lord’s glory, are being transformed into his image with ever-increasing glory, which comes from the Lord, who is the Spirit. (2 Corinthians 3:18) The image is of vision—of seeing face to face. In ancient times, according to Paul, people had covered their faces when approaching God. They could not see him, could not understand him. There was no intimate relationship. They longed to cross that chasm. My eyes shall see him, mine and not another, echo the heart-wrenching words of Job. In the biblical story, humans were made in the image of God, made to reflect God’s glory to all creation. Thus, to see God dimly, through a covering, was to be disconnected from what we really are. It was to fall short of the glory of God. Now we see as in mirror—then we shall see face to face. In Christ, according to Paul, that covering has been ripped away. Now, we can look at God face to face. Now, in contemplating God, we are transformed into a vision of God. Every relationship transforms us. We become part of the other person, and they become part of us. We become increasingly like each other. The more clearly we see the other person, the more deeply they become part of who we are. To see God face-to-face is to be in a relationship deeper and more intimate than you can imagine. It is to know that God is within you, transforming you into God’s image and glory. The desire to look upon God, to have that relationship fill you and transform you in every way, to feel it as deep as love, and as strong as power—is what this song is about. Be Thou my Vision, O Lord of my heart; Naught be all else to me, save that Thou art. Thou my best Thought, by day or by night, Waking or sleeping, Thy presence my light. Be Thou my Wisdom, and Thou my true Word; I ever with Thee and Thou with me, Lord; Thou my great Father, I Thy true son; Thou in me dwelling, and I with Thee one. Be Thou my battle Shield, Sword for the fight; Be Thou my Dignity, Thou my Delight; Thou my soul’s Shelter, Thou my high Tower: Raise Thou me heavenward, O Power of my power. Riches I heed not, nor man’s empty praise, Thou mine Inheritance, now and always: Thou and Thou only, first in my heart, High King of Heaven, my Treasure Thou art. High King of Heaven, my victory won, May I reach Heaven’s joys, O bright Heaven’s Sun! Heart of my own heart, whatever befall, Still be my Vision, O Ruler of all.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://res.cloudinary.com/micahredding/image/upload/v1608740634/blonde-woman-in-meadow-looking-at-sunset_c89gmf.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://res.cloudinary.com/micahredding/image/upload/v1608740634/blonde-woman-in-meadow-looking-at-sunset_c89gmf.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Tower of Babel</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/tower-of-babel/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Tower of Babel" /><published>2018-05-11T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-05-11T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/tower-of-babel</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/tower-of-babel/"><![CDATA[<p>Perhaps no biblical story has captivated people’s imaginations like the Tower of Babel. In this story, a group of people get together to build a tower tall enough to reach heaven—from which they intend to launch an all-out war on God himself. God sees what the people are building, and furious at their hubris, destroys the tower, and condemns humanity to the Earth.</p>

<p>Or something like that. That’s not really in the Bible, but it’s what a lot of people hear and repeat. It’s almost like they mashed up the Bible with Icarus, Prometheus, and Jack &amp; the Beanstalk.</p>

<p>And every time someone feels like humanity is advancing too fast, they pull out this story, and try to slap people down with it.</p>

<p>In doing so, they may be unwittingly enacting the Sin of Babel themselves.</p>

<h3 id="the-tower-to-nowhere">The Tower to Nowhere</h3>

<p>In the Bible, the Tower of Babel has a context. When God created humanity, he created them in his image, made them godlike (Genesis 1:26-28), and instructed them to participate in his work, creating and cultivating the life of the world, just as he had done.</p>

<p>Growing into that immense role would take time, though. The very first thing humanity had to do was to become a planetary species.</p>

<p>These are God’s first instructions to humanity: be fruitful and multiply (so there would be more humans to help), and <em>fill the earth</em>—so that the work could be truly global in scope.</p>

<p>God had given these instructions in Genesis 1, but after Noah’s flood, the mission was relaunched, and God reiterated these instructions to the people emerging from the Ark:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Then God blessed Noah and his sons, saying to them, “Be fruitful and increase in number and <strong>fill the earth</strong>.” (Genesis 9:1)</p>
</blockquote>

<p>And that’s exactly what humans started doing.</p>

<p>But then someone had a different idea.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Come, let us build ourselves a city, with a tower that reaches to the heavens, so that we may make a name for ourselves; otherwise we will be <strong>scattered over the face of the whole earth</strong>.” (Genesis 11:4)</p>
</blockquote>

<p>There’s a lot going on here. Notice, first of all, they’re not setting out to build a tower, they’re setting out to build a <em>city</em>.</p>

<p>In the book of Genesis, this is a red flag—so far, the good guys are nomads, spreading out across the landscape, <em>filling the earth</em>, while the bad guys are city-builders, murderous tyrants trying to batten down the hatches, surround themselves with walls, and hold their ground.</p>

<p>The Bible’s first city-builder? Cain, right after he slew Abel.</p>

<p>Sure enough, there’s something very similar going on here. Why do they want this city, and why does this city need to have a tower?</p>

<p>According to their own account, they’re doing this to make a name for themselves, so that they can avoid being <em>scattered over the face of the earth</em>.</p>

<p>It’s a brilliant idea. If they make the most famous city ever, no one will ever want to leave. People will be so proud of where they’re from, no one will ever venture out to explore new possibilities or new places.</p>

<p>And here’s the crux of the problem. They were <em>supposed</em> to be exploring new possibilities and new places. God had <em>just told them</em> to scatter over the face of the earth. That was part of their mission, part of what they needed to do to keep growing, so they could become the planetary species God had always intended them to be.</p>

<p>God wanted humanity to grow—these people wanted things to stay the same.</p>

<p>They were rejecting God’s mission of ongoing change and growth, and choosing instead to aggressively defend the ways things were.</p>

<p><strong><a href="https://www.micahredding.com/blog/tower-of-babel" title="#tweet-this">Defending the way things are, at the expense of a better future, is the Sin of Babel.</a></strong></p>

<p>-</p>

<h3 id="gods-answer-to-tyranny">God’s Answer to Tyranny</h3>

<blockquote>
  <p>But the Lord came down to see the city and the tower the people were building. The Lord said, “If as one people speaking the same language they have begun to do this, then nothing they plan to do will be impossible for them.” (Genesis 11:5-6)</p>
</blockquote>

<p>They had started work on their project, and sure enough, God confirms that humanity was powerful enough to build these kinds of things. After all, God had <em>made</em> them that powerful.</p>

<p>So what’s God’s problem with this?</p>

<p>According to what God says, the problem is not the tower—it’s that this tower indicates that <em>the rest</em> of their plans are within reach.</p>

<p>Including the plan to never, ever leave. If they don’t want to fill the earth, they won’t.</p>

<p>The grand project God intended for the human race will come to an end right here, as they get absorbed in a project specifically designed to thwart God’s intentions for continued growth.</p>

<p>This wasn’t just a one-time issue. Even if God stopped this project, the next project would spring up, and the next, and the next. Humanity seems intent on defending the ways things are, at the expense of the much greater future God intends.</p>

<p>What kind of society engages in grandiose building projects just to make itself famous? What kind of society is determined to make sure no one ever leaves? What kind of society would every Jewish family think of, when hearing a name that sounds like the root word of “Babylon”?</p>

<p><em>Tyranny.</em></p>

<p>Over and over in the biblical story, tyranny is what stands opposed to God’s plans for humanity. The tyranny of Egypt, Babylon, and Rome stand against newness and growth and life. Right here in the beginning, we’re seeing just how destructive this kind of tyranny can be—if nothing is done, it will erase the glorious future of the human race.</p>

<p>So God comes up with a plan of his own.</p>

<p>God will introduce linguistic diversity into the human race. Diversity will disrupt tyranny, making it hard for there to be any single source of power. Without a single source of power, there will be a world of plurality and difference, and no one will ever be able to completely eradicate change.</p>

<p><strong><a href="https://www.micahredding.com/blog/tower-of-babel" title="#tweet-this">Diversity is God’s answer to tyranny.</a></strong></p>

<p>That’s exactly what God does, introducing a diversity of languages. And so, as the story sums up, the project grinds to a halt, people go back to spreading and exploring, and humanity is <em>scattered over the face of the whole earth</em> (Genesis 11:9).</p>

<p>Just as God always intended.</p>

<p>It’s remarkable what’s not here. God doesn’t destroy their tower. God doesn’t forbid them from building new towers. God doesn’t even forbid them from building cities—though a righteous city-builder will take a few more generations to come along. God doesn’t show any indication of being furious with them, let alone being afraid they’re about to storm his gates.</p>

<p>The whole story is about this: Will humanity continue to spread out and grow, as God intended, or will they build power structures that defend the way things are, and resist the ongoing process of change?</p>

<p>God, seeing that humans keep being drawn to oppressive power structures, introduces diversity as an answer to tyranny. God’s plan works, these growth-rejecting projects are thwarted, and humanity goes back to growing into a planetary species.</p>

<h3 id="reversing-babel">Reversing Babel</h3>

<p>That’s the end of the Babel story in Genesis. But it’s not really the end of the story in the Bible.</p>

<p>In the New Testament, when the Christian church is launched on the day of Pentecost, the Tower of Babel is symbolically reversed. Where Babel marks the introduction of the confusion of different languages, Pentecost marks the beginning of a new unity, where everyone can understand each other.</p>

<p>Pentecost doesn’t do this by eliminating all the diversity God introduced at Babel. Instead, it does this by equipping people to understand and appreciate that diversity. The brand-new Christians find that they can communicate in different languages, and understand people from far different backgrounds.</p>

<p>Babel was a moment when humanity turned in on itself, and threatened to become tyrannical, self-absorbed, and stagnant. With the introduction of diversity, God saved humanity from tyranny, and gave it back its mission.</p>

<p>But it came with a downside. Diversity cost humanity its unity.</p>

<p>At Pentecost, that dilemma is finally answered. In partnership with God, we can bring about greater unity through—and not in spite of—our diversity. In partnership with God, we can learn to understand and appreciate each other’s differences, and be stronger for it.</p>

<p>And that’s all part of God’s plan for us to move beyond the way things are, toward the much greater future God intends.</p>]]></content><author><name>Micah Redding</name></author><category term="Theology" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Perhaps no biblical story has captivated people’s imaginations like the Tower of Babel. In this story, a group of people get together to build a tower tall enough to reach heaven—from which they intend to launch an all-out war on God himself. God sees what the people are building, and furious at their hubris, destroys the tower, and condemns humanity to the Earth. Or something like that. That’s not really in the Bible, but it’s what a lot of people hear and repeat. It’s almost like they mashed up the Bible with Icarus, Prometheus, and Jack &amp; the Beanstalk. And every time someone feels like humanity is advancing too fast, they pull out this story, and try to slap people down with it. In doing so, they may be unwittingly enacting the Sin of Babel themselves. The Tower to Nowhere In the Bible, the Tower of Babel has a context. When God created humanity, he created them in his image, made them godlike (Genesis 1:26-28), and instructed them to participate in his work, creating and cultivating the life of the world, just as he had done. Growing into that immense role would take time, though. The very first thing humanity had to do was to become a planetary species. These are God’s first instructions to humanity: be fruitful and multiply (so there would be more humans to help), and fill the earth—so that the work could be truly global in scope. God had given these instructions in Genesis 1, but after Noah’s flood, the mission was relaunched, and God reiterated these instructions to the people emerging from the Ark: Then God blessed Noah and his sons, saying to them, “Be fruitful and increase in number and fill the earth.” (Genesis 9:1) And that’s exactly what humans started doing. But then someone had a different idea. “Come, let us build ourselves a city, with a tower that reaches to the heavens, so that we may make a name for ourselves; otherwise we will be scattered over the face of the whole earth.” (Genesis 11:4) There’s a lot going on here. Notice, first of all, they’re not setting out to build a tower, they’re setting out to build a city. In the book of Genesis, this is a red flag—so far, the good guys are nomads, spreading out across the landscape, filling the earth, while the bad guys are city-builders, murderous tyrants trying to batten down the hatches, surround themselves with walls, and hold their ground. The Bible’s first city-builder? Cain, right after he slew Abel. Sure enough, there’s something very similar going on here. Why do they want this city, and why does this city need to have a tower? According to their own account, they’re doing this to make a name for themselves, so that they can avoid being scattered over the face of the earth. It’s a brilliant idea. If they make the most famous city ever, no one will ever want to leave. People will be so proud of where they’re from, no one will ever venture out to explore new possibilities or new places. And here’s the crux of the problem. They were supposed to be exploring new possibilities and new places. God had just told them to scatter over the face of the earth. That was part of their mission, part of what they needed to do to keep growing, so they could become the planetary species God had always intended them to be. God wanted humanity to grow—these people wanted things to stay the same. They were rejecting God’s mission of ongoing change and growth, and choosing instead to aggressively defend the ways things were. Defending the way things are, at the expense of a better future, is the Sin of Babel. - God’s Answer to Tyranny But the Lord came down to see the city and the tower the people were building. The Lord said, “If as one people speaking the same language they have begun to do this, then nothing they plan to do will be impossible for them.” (Genesis 11:5-6) They had started work on their project, and sure enough, God confirms that humanity was powerful enough to build these kinds of things. After all, God had made them that powerful. So what’s God’s problem with this? According to what God says, the problem is not the tower—it’s that this tower indicates that the rest of their plans are within reach. Including the plan to never, ever leave. If they don’t want to fill the earth, they won’t. The grand project God intended for the human race will come to an end right here, as they get absorbed in a project specifically designed to thwart God’s intentions for continued growth. This wasn’t just a one-time issue. Even if God stopped this project, the next project would spring up, and the next, and the next. Humanity seems intent on defending the ways things are, at the expense of the much greater future God intends. What kind of society engages in grandiose building projects just to make itself famous? What kind of society is determined to make sure no one ever leaves? What kind of society would every Jewish family think of, when hearing a name that sounds like the root word of “Babylon”? Tyranny. Over and over in the biblical story, tyranny is what stands opposed to God’s plans for humanity. The tyranny of Egypt, Babylon, and Rome stand against newness and growth and life. Right here in the beginning, we’re seeing just how destructive this kind of tyranny can be—if nothing is done, it will erase the glorious future of the human race. So God comes up with a plan of his own. God will introduce linguistic diversity into the human race. Diversity will disrupt tyranny, making it hard for there to be any single source of power. Without a single source of power, there will be a world of plurality and difference, and no one will ever be able to completely eradicate change. Diversity is God’s answer to tyranny. That’s exactly what God does, introducing a diversity of languages. And so, as the story sums up, the project grinds to a halt, people go back to spreading and exploring, and humanity is scattered over the face of the whole earth (Genesis 11:9). Just as God always intended. It’s remarkable what’s not here. God doesn’t destroy their tower. God doesn’t forbid them from building new towers. God doesn’t even forbid them from building cities—though a righteous city-builder will take a few more generations to come along. God doesn’t show any indication of being furious with them, let alone being afraid they’re about to storm his gates. The whole story is about this: Will humanity continue to spread out and grow, as God intended, or will they build power structures that defend the way things are, and resist the ongoing process of change? God, seeing that humans keep being drawn to oppressive power structures, introduces diversity as an answer to tyranny. God’s plan works, these growth-rejecting projects are thwarted, and humanity goes back to growing into a planetary species. Reversing Babel That’s the end of the Babel story in Genesis. But it’s not really the end of the story in the Bible. In the New Testament, when the Christian church is launched on the day of Pentecost, the Tower of Babel is symbolically reversed. Where Babel marks the introduction of the confusion of different languages, Pentecost marks the beginning of a new unity, where everyone can understand each other. Pentecost doesn’t do this by eliminating all the diversity God introduced at Babel. Instead, it does this by equipping people to understand and appreciate that diversity. The brand-new Christians find that they can communicate in different languages, and understand people from far different backgrounds. Babel was a moment when humanity turned in on itself, and threatened to become tyrannical, self-absorbed, and stagnant. With the introduction of diversity, God saved humanity from tyranny, and gave it back its mission. But it came with a downside. Diversity cost humanity its unity. At Pentecost, that dilemma is finally answered. In partnership with God, we can bring about greater unity through—and not in spite of—our diversity. In partnership with God, we can learn to understand and appreciate each other’s differences, and be stronger for it. And that’s all part of God’s plan for us to move beyond the way things are, toward the much greater future God intends.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://res.cloudinary.com/micahredding/image/upload/v1526049036/iqnbl1ls8zem4rcgpole.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://res.cloudinary.com/micahredding/image/upload/v1526049036/iqnbl1ls8zem4rcgpole.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>